<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An astrologicall prediction of the occurrances in England, part of the yeers 1648. 1649. 1650. concerning these particulars, viz. 1. The effects depending upon the late conjunction of the two malevolent planets Saturn and Mars. 2. What successe may be expected from the present intended treaty between his Majesty and the Parliament. 3. The standing or falling of this Parliament, and the army under the command of his Excellency the Lord Fairfax. 4. Our imminent disturbances generally handled, together with many contingencies to the whole kingdom, London especially. 5. The product of the Scots army: with some observations upon Duke Hamiltons nativity. 6. What may succeed the apparition of three suns in Lancashire, seen of many, the 28. Febr. last. By William Lilly, student in Astrologie.</title>
            <author>Lilly, William, 1602-1681.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 212KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88278</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864500</idno>
  <idno type="VID">116730</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240904110</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2211</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E462_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205058</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864500</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99864500e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88278)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116730)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 74:E462[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An astrologicall prediction of the occurrances in England, part of the yeers 1648. 1649. 1650. concerning these particulars, viz. 1. The effects depending upon the late conjunction of the two malevolent planets Saturn and Mars. 2. What successe may be expected from the present intended treaty between his Majesty and the Parliament. 3. The standing or falling of this Parliament, and the army under the command of his Excellency the Lord Fairfax. 4. Our imminent disturbances generally handled, together with many contingencies to the whole kingdom, London especially. 5. The product of the Scots army: with some observations upon Duke Hamiltons nativity. 6. What may succeed the apparition of three suns in Lancashire, seen of many, the 28. Febr. last. By William Lilly, student in Astrologie.</title>
                  <author>Lilly, William, 1602-1681.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 71, [1] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.B. for John Partridge and Humfrey Blunden, and are to be sold in Blackfriers going into Carterlane, and at the Castle in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept. ye 4".</note>
                  <note>In this edition, line 13 of title page ends: un-.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">London (England) --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116730:1"/>
            <p>AN Astrologicall Prediction OF THE Occurrances in England, Part of the Yeers 1648. 1649. 1650.</p>
            <p>Concerning these Particulars, <hi>Viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The effects depending upon the late conjunction of the two malevolent Planets <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. What successe may be expected from the present intended Treaty between his Majesty and the Parliament.</item>
                  <item>3. The standing or falling of this Parliament, and the Army un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the command of his Excellency the Lord <hi>Fairfax.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. Our imminent disturbances generally handled, together with many contingencies to the whole Kingdom, <hi>London</hi> espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially.</item>
                  <item>5. The product of the <hi>Scots</hi> Army: With some Observations upon Duke <hi>Hamiltons</hi> Nativity.</item>
                  <item>6. What may succeed the apparition of three SUNS in <hi>Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire,</hi> seen of many, the 28. <hi>Febr.</hi> last.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By WILLIAM LILLY, Student in <hi>Astrologie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON: Printed by <hi>T. B.</hi> for <hi>John Partridge</hi> and <hi>Humfrey Blunden,</hi> and are to be sold in <hi>Blackfriers</hi> going into <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlane,</hi> and at the <hi>Castle</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:116730:2"/>
            <head>To the right honorable, the <hi>Knights, Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens,</hi> and <hi>Burgesses</hi> of the House of <hi>Commons</hi> in this PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Unwearied SIRS:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Ery great is that confidence (we the people) repose in your wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; our expectations rise high, &amp; we strōgly impregnated in hope of a safe delivery. There are yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining an hūdred fifty thousand honest hearts, whose fidelities, neither your adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sities or prosperities have depressed or elevated; these stand unanimously resolved to expire their last breath in defence of your Persons and our owne just Priviledges. Nor are they deterred ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the <hi>Scottish,</hi> City or Malignant faction from a just adherance unto you; and yet they well know, how, that most of your persons are designed for slaughter, your Estates disposed, and that Army under the Command of his Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy predesigned for destruction (I mean by your
<pb facs="tcp:116730:3"/> Enemies;) the Liberty of the Commons of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> decreed to an everlasting Tyranny. <hi>Anglicus</hi> your most humble servant, having but a few Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nements, by the Rents wherof he subsists, his hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses are divided, and possession expected. Oh most noble souls look about you, let a sharp and sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <hi>Index expurgatorius</hi> cleanse your own House first, then the Kingdome of the <hi>Scottish</hi> faction. Divine providence hath already in part, and will in time wholly subject unto you all that rise a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst you. Cherish and countenance this Army, else you perish and the Kingdom is undone God hath punished the perfidious <hi>Scot</hi> already; he is now lifting up his hand of vengeance against our own <hi>English</hi> disturbers. All <hi>Europe</hi> expect the issue of your Treaty with his MAjESTY; we beg of God that his MAjESTY may have from you Condiscentions honourable, and that you may be answered from Him with Grants conform to reason and justice.</p>
            <p>God direct you in all your Consultations, and destroy your private and publique enemies. Let not your hearts fail, for you are ordained by God to act high matters. He that presents these lines unto you, is the Kingdoms and</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble servant, <hi>W. LILLY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:116730:3"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD Almighty, who loves upright m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, hath delivered <hi>Colchester</hi> to his Excellency the Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> subdued the trecherous <hi>Scot,</hi> and their Generall <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milton,</hi> and all the malignant Commanders, unto his servant, Lievtenant generall <hi>Cromwell;</hi> let <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> love these men, and take care of their Army.</p>
            <p>What in <hi>1644, 1645,</hi> and <hi>1646.</hi> I publickly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vised unto his Majesty, as most conducing for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms peace, whilest he had many strong defenced Cities, Castles and Towns in his possession, and whilest he was Master of very considerable Armyes abroad in the Field, <hi>viz.</hi> That he would come unto <hi>London</hi> and comply with this present Parliament. You see now, after the expence of so much Blood and Treasure, that very advice and councell is likely to be the most assured means of re-estating him in his pristine Authority, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>His Majesty was not ordained to be fortunate in War, it's not a gift given to every Prince. I pray God blesse this present intended Treaty, so much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired, with a successe answerable to the integrity of his Majesties heart, and the wholsome, deliberate Consultations of an indefatigable Parliament. In the interim whereof, and during the Treaties continuance, yea, and after, let all the Counties of this Kingdom unite as one man, to engage against all that rise against the Parliament, and these barbarous and perjured <hi>Scots</hi> that are entered already our Kingdom, and those who are also approaching, not to re-estate his Majesty (as themselves cunningly pretend) but purposely to steal our Goods, ravish our Wives, enslave our Persons, inherit our Possessions and Birth-rights, remain here in <hi>England,</hi> and everlastingly to inhabit among us: Those who plead the Scottish civility, or call them Brethren in affront of the Parliament, I wish their estates in the North, <hi>Jockey</hi> and <hi>Moggy</hi> and their beggarly brats quartering upon it, &amp;c.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:116730:4"/>
            <p>Yet we must not blame the whole Nation for the trecheries of this prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Party of <hi>Scots:</hi> it's known, many religious men of that Nation, both Lords, Gentlemen and Ministers, from their very souls abhor this wicked Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my lately under <hi>Hamilton,</hi> my Pen shall write nothing but honour of those men, for I love them; and that miraculous honest <hi>Scot</hi> Generall <hi>Lesley.</hi> A wicked Party of our own in <hi>England</hi> have brought them in amongst us, and our very Ministers have many of them been active herein: It's observed, how little the Parliament and Kingdom are beholding unto them, for how many of that Tribe, I pray you, did any man hear in their Pulpits desire a blessing from God upon our Forces in the North, who went to fight them, or a curse upon the <hi>Scots?</hi> or which of them bestowed one blessing upon his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies Army besieging our malignant enemies in <hi>Colchester?</hi> Oh these Priests! this sinfull people of <hi>Levi</hi> do hunger and thirst after the fat flesh-pots of Episcopacy! if they were assured that Deans and Chapters Lands should not be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etled on the Church, God then knowes what Religion they would be of. Wo unto you Priests.</p>
            <p>And though <hi>Cornelius,</hi> an eminent Reformado, endures no Ʋsury, yet give him consideration for his money, and he pockets it; not for himself, I trust, oh no Sir, 'tis for Orphans, little children full forty yeers old. But I leave these men and proceed to the Laity, and desire the blessing of Almighty God upon the Counties of <hi>Essex</hi> and <hi>Suffolk,</hi> who so freely and honourably contributed assistance unto the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> in besieging <hi>Colchester.</hi> And let it be eternized for ever in the Records of fame, the gallantry of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Lancashire,</hi> whose Lyon-like spirited men fought eagerly against the <hi>Scots,</hi> and who so willingly assisted the Parliament formerly, and now also at this present. I exceedingly prayse God, that my native County of <hi>Leceister</hi> now in the Parliaments late ebbing, did so unanimously and cheerfully appear and in such numbers, for assistance of the publike good: If they will fight, I will write. Nor is the regaining of <hi>Tinmouth</hi> by Sir <hi>Authur Haslerig</hi> our Country man, a service lesse then very honourable.</p>
            <p>But let us now to the Discourse ensuing, which was in part finished some weeks since, but not intended for the Presse. I foresaw the many and sad de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections since happened unto the Parliament, I hoped they would have been lesse; I was sensible of a divine Providence overpowering the Stars, else the better Party in <hi>Scotland</hi> had prevailed, &amp; we had not this yeer been invaded: but God reserves unto himself the unchangeable Decrees of Kingdoms, and I perceive hy his sometimes checking or retarding, at other times his hasty put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in execution the influence of the Planets, that man hath not yet attained
<pb facs="tcp:116730:4"/> so full a perfection in <hi>Astrology,</hi> whereby he might without fallacy give a determinable and positive judgement: for though I was very doubtfull of the Scottish faith, all along in <hi>Anglicus 1648.</hi> as any may perceive: yet forasmuch as it did not appear fully unto me this Scottish defection, I was sparing, perhaps my weaknesse (which I willingly acknowledge) might be occasioned by my affection, overballanced with their former merit, well hoping Religion, which can onely bind man to honesty and faith, would have prevailed, and so it did in the Ministery and some others, but in the generality, it seems Religion is made but the <hi>Scots</hi> stalking-horse. Their fate I hope is rightly predicted in my Epistle, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I retract an errour as willingly as I write a truth: I still stand for Monarchy, I wish the Treaty perfected for all our goods; and verily I hope his Majesty, now wearied with the sad condition of life attending him and his whole family, and well perceiving the fruitlesse successe of Armes, and other Designs, intended for his enlargement by his Friends, will wave such strict Propositions, as in former Treaties he might have insisted upon; he hath good reason so to do, for really had not the <hi>Scots</hi> malicious Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners bogled and jugled with his Majesty, and protested against our Parliaments three Propositions, I am well assured his Majesty had been re-estated ere this, enjoyed his Queen, and seen all his Progeny about him, and rejoyced with his Subjects of this Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> in peace and tranquility; for he was not uninclinable of himself at that time, but was misled by those Commissioners ill councell given unto him: so that the sole occasion of our second troubles, and of our present Wars and distractions in the Kingdom, was solely occasioned by the plottings and Agents of the <hi>Scottish</hi> Commissioners, and their Factors in the City, with Citizens, and some collapsed Members of Parliament: But God hath in part rewarded their Army.</p>
            <p>The Kingdom shall now see by the willing condiscention of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament unto some things formerly controverted, how willing they are to compose differences by a Treaty, contrary to some yelping fellows discourses, so that I hope well of this Treaty.</p>
            <p>Some will expect I should give reasons for this wet Weather, the like having not happened this many yeers. I am not at present provided for that Discourse: Onely <hi>Saturn</hi> being now in his <hi>Perigeon,</hi> is as neer the earth as he can be, and meeting with the <hi>conjunction</hi> of <hi>Mars</hi> in the
<pb facs="tcp:116730:5"/> Sign <hi>Gemini,</hi> neer many fixed Stars of contrary nature, might occasion this wet Weather: But if it be from any naturall causes, we may then hope of comfortable serene Weather, even from the beginning of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> and so forward: If the immediate finger of God be against us, I must submit.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Corner-house over against</hi> Strand-bridge, <date>
                     <hi>Aug. 22. 1648.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>WILLIAM LILLY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116730:5"/>
            <head>An ASTROLOGICALL Prediction concerning these present TIMES; Probably conjecturing the successe of the Treaty now inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded betwixt his Majesty and Parliament: Also of the SCOTTISH Army now in <hi>England, &amp;c.</hi> DEO, REGI, PATRIAE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HO meddles with the actions of any Kingdom or Country by way of <hi>Astrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall</hi> prediction (even in a calm season, when no storms or distractions are visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) shall in composing the work it self undergo much study, great travell and labour of minde, and after publication of his endeavours (how beneficiall soe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they may prove) shall not fail to receive a censure most aspersive, harsh, and criticall in his reputatation, from the Vogue of ordinary people. Both which we have found expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimentally verified, upon our preceding labours, which we ever intended for common good, expecting no more then publike reception, and to be rightly, and not sinisterly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood: how great our industry hath been, whilest we walked in those uncouth paths no former Author had trodden in, we leave to the consideratiō of men learned, &amp; how many unjust scandals and afronts, both in fame and person, we have week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly suffered, by the impudent Pens of scribling and prophane <hi>Mercuries,</hi> the whole Kingdom is too too much informed. But did these ungracious <hi>Pamphleteers</hi> understand how willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I read my self abused in their smutty sheets, they would as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suredly continue their disaffections unto me, which trouble me so much, that I account it my greatest glory (themselves being bad men) to be in emnity with, and hatred of them.</p>
            <p>Some yeers since, God called me from an happy Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plative
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116730:6"/> life, sufficiently pleasing to my quiet <hi>Genius</hi> (being content with an Angle in my Hand, a Book in my Study, a Flower in my Garden) and both enheightned and enlightned my spirit to be active in the Common Cause of the Kingdom, and brought me to <hi>London,</hi> where, in 1644. I began a new manner of <hi>Astrologie,</hi> heretofore either not known to the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients,</hi> or else willingly omitted in their Writings: it cannot be denied, but that I began to write and appear for the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and Kingdom in their most sad condition, at what time I must have expected immediate destruction, if God had not owned our Cause, and blessed our predictions with Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentary successe. Let these things passe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Having wearied my self of late in our <hi>Introduction</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glicus</hi> 1648. and finding no return but reproach, I had not any further will or desire to engage longer in these <hi>nationall</hi> dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, wherein how dangerous it is to speak all and every truth my now dear experience tels me: I was, I say, therefore resolved a little to repose after my former wearisome studies, hoping, and being in full expectation some of our Kingdoms <hi>Astrologers</hi> (wherewith we now begin to abound) would enter upon this quarrell, and either bid defiance to our adversaries, or second those my former weak Labours: but herein my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation was frustrate, and poor <hi>Anglicus</hi> must yet a while stand single, untill Providence ordain him a fit <hi>Second.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Towards the latter end of <hi>March</hi> last, Master <hi>Jeremy Shakerly</hi> (one very learned and expert in the <hi>Mathematticks</hi>) wholly unknown to me, sent me the Letter following, with the <hi>Type</hi> of the three <hi>Suns</hi> ready drawn, as also the Scheam of heaven, performed by himself; his earnest entreaty to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish my thoughts upon these Appearances, I hitherto have refused: I also have denied many of my friends desires, who have importuned as much; but at last, I was so daringly and unjustly provoked by some diurnall slippery <hi>Mercuries,</hi> who perceiving my continued silence, have not failed weekly to stain my <hi>Monethly predictions</hi> with falsnesse, and advance their own <hi>Pigmean Chymera's</hi> (which themselves call <hi>Astrologicall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions</hi>) yea forsooth, they by their <hi>significant constellations of heaven,</hi> could predict and divine no lesse then a present disso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, and inevitable destruction of our present Parliament,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116730:6"/> and of all the honest and well affected party adhering unto them: and when, I pray you, must this be? for they (being confident) appointed a certain time; nay, they fall upon a day, or within three dayes at the most; and this day, in <hi>good sooth,</hi> was nominated the 28. day of <hi>Iune</hi> last, or else certainly on some of the three subsequent dayes: But see the errour and madnesse of these Lyars, for neither potentially or actually have any of these old Wives fables had effect, &amp;c. Our Parliament lives, our Army subsists and thrives, the good people fear nothing, no threats. These men also imputed unto my passive silence an ambiguous fear of our Causes declinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and in plain language <hi>(ad faciem)</hi> tell me, Had there been but one crum of comfort in the <hi>Planets</hi> or <hi>Stars,</hi> or any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable, <hi>auspitious</hi> or promising aspects unto our side, they wondered I could now be silent, having been formerly so great a <hi>Champion</hi> and stickler for the Parliament and Army. They also upbraid my predictions with the <hi>Scottish</hi> infidelity, and object my too too honourable mention of them; but do I since <hi>Mayes</hi> predictions once mention that people; and did not the godly Party of <hi>Scotland,</hi> even in that Moneth, declare against this wicked Army now entred our Kingdom? and was not that an honourable act? &amp;c. To be short, 'tis the villanous Pens of these abusive knaves, whom we stile <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> that have enforced my <hi>fatall</hi> Pen sooner then intended; I am still principled as formerly, and am a lover and desirer of his Majesty to reign, and of his Posterity to succeed him, and of the continuance of <hi>Monarchy</hi> in this Island; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the times, or preferments, or self ends have varied many, <hi>Me</hi> neither have bribes nor rewards corrupted, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulnesse moved to <hi>retrogradation;</hi> with the former I have been tempted, of the later I am sensible, &amp;c. <hi>A love princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <hi>Worthy Sir, and ever honoured Friend:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">The occasion of writing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the three Suns.</note>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>HOw fruitfull time in prodigious issues shews her self, and in what variety of appearance nature is arayed, I wish we might rather learn from ancient Histories, then that our own knowledge should histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie the same; and better were it for us to lay claim to this truth, by the Legacies of Antiquity, then that our own eyes should enstate us in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116730:7"/> possession hereof: But since it pleased God to make me an eye witnesse of an unusuall accident, I would not conceal it from you, because both mine own duty, and the importunate desires of others, have induced me thereto.</p>
                  <p>On <hi>Monday</hi> the <hi>28.</hi> of <hi>February</hi> last, there arose with the Sun two Parelii, on either side one, their distance from him was by estimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, about ten degrees; they continued still of the same distance from the Zenith, or height above the Horizon, that the Sun did; and from the parts averse to the Sun, there seemed to issue out certain bright rays, not unlike those which the Sun sendeth from behind a cloud, but brighter. The parts of these Parelii which were toward the Sun, were of a mixt colour, wherein green and red were most predominant: A little above them was a thin Rainbow, scarcely discernable, of a bright colour, with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cave towards the Sun, and the ends thereof seeming to touch the Parelii: Above that, in a cleer diaphanous ayre, appeared another co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>spicuous Rainbow, beautified with divers colours; it was as neer as I could dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern to the Zenith; it seemed of something a lesser radius then the other, they being back to back, yet a pretty way between. At or neer the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent time of the full Moon, they vanished, leaving abundance of ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and amazement in those that saw them: Divers whose thoughts laboured with fearfull expectations, desired my opinion thereof; I endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to give them such satisfaction as I could, and told them, These Appearances were no other then such as proceeded from naturall causes, being but the brightnesse of the Suns beams, from a cloud reflected on the earth, and that the ancient times were not onely witnesses of the like, but even our own times: Yet will not all calm the distracted cogitations of those that beheld it. Good Sir, at my request, at the Countries re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest, be pleased to publish your Astrologicall judgement hereupon, and assure your self that what is done for the satisfaction of many, will also procure you the well wishes of many.</p>
                  <p>I have also sent you these two Figures exactly erected, whereof you may make use in your judgements; the first for the new Moon preceding the Appearance, the other for the beginning of the Appearance.</p>
                  <p>Thus with my service a thousand times remembred, I onely tell you that I am</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours, till I cease to be JER. SHAKERLEY.</signed>
                     <dateline>Pendle-forrest <hi>in</hi> Lancashire, <date>March <hi>4. 1648.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:116730:7"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of an apparition of three suns and two rainbows</figDesc>
               <head>Binorum Pareliorum <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Feb 28 1647/48</head>
            </figure>
            <p>God many wayes in these last times (though not by prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy) yet discovers and signifies his intentions unto us, and espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in and at those times when his heavy judgements are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent upon us; witnesse the many and frequent Apparences of severall <hi>Prodigies</hi> seen in this Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> within these four or five yeers, the like whereof for number are not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in any, either ancient or modern History, so that I might weary the <hi>Reader,</hi> should I but mention the severall Letters which from sundry parts of this Kingdom have come to my hands, some mentioning strange <hi>sights</hi> in the ayre; others, Men fighting therein; others, Guns shooting; others relating of three Moons; others, the <hi>apparition</hi> of two Suns; some send<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me Letters, and including therein some part of that Corn which was rained down from heaven, &amp;c. I forbear all further discourse hereof, <hi>assuring</hi> the Kingdom, these <hi>Prodigies</hi> are the <hi>Premonitors,</hi> and assured infallible <hi>Messengers</hi> of Gods wrath against the whole Kingdom, for our wicked transgressions, &amp;c. God give us peace and grace to repent.</p>
            <p>The Method I intend to follow in judging what the three
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116730:8"/> Suns, now mentioned, may signifie, is twofold: the first is <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storicall</hi> and generall; the second, <hi>Astrologicall,</hi> and more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular to our present Condition and Nation; after which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows a Diary of the Weather for one Moneth, after the day of the appearance of the Suns, taken by a learned hand and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of quality in <hi>N.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tot homines, tot sententiae,</hi> so many men, so many opinions: There are some men, of whom we read in <hi>Bodin,</hi> that do affirm, There were never seen any <hi>Mock-Suns</hi> or <hi>Parelii;</hi> and so great a confidence they had of their own muddy judgemens, that they reputed the report of such Apparitions no better then old Wives fables, and those who mentioned them, no better then Drunkards, deluded with idle <hi>phantasmes:</hi> But it was well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted by <hi>Resta,</hi> pag. 577. <hi>At potius ebrius, qui serio hec cogitat. viz.</hi> He is the most Drunkard that beleeves no such things. These men are like those who objected, That the Apostles were drunk with strong Wine at Whitsontide, it being then but the third hour of the day. <hi>Parelii</hi> or mock Suns more usually appear in the morning, then any other time of the day, and men are not very oft drunk so soon. It was rightly, I conceive, understood by Saint <hi>Augustine,</hi> Epist. 80. ad Hesechium. <hi>Aliquando has appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentias esse miraculosas, &amp; tum non opus est naturae vires expendere, ut earum causas demus.</hi> These Appearances are usually miraculous, and then why shall we endeavour to finde out a naturall cause for them, &amp;c. And really I am induced to think they are super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall, and appear not as enforced from any naturall Cause but are framed by the <hi>Guardian-Angels</hi> or Intelligencees of that Kingdō where they appear, into that or those forms we see them, purposely to admonish the <hi>Inhabitants</hi> of material accidents sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly to break forth amongst them: the <hi>Ancients,</hi> who would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly have givē us the naturall causes of them are so discrepant one to another in opinion, that no conclusion can be had from their Writings. <hi>Seneca</hi> will have them thick clouds, light and shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. <hi>Vitellio</hi> will have the matter be <hi>Nubem equalem secundum sua specula, neque densiorem, neque rariorem, neque plus aquosam, neque minus secundum suas partes, non aquosam neque nigram, vicinam tamen aquae.</hi> An equall cloud according to its <hi>mirrours,</hi> neither more dense, or rare, or more watery, or lesse, according to its parts; not watry, or black, yet very neer to water. Thus he. Others will have them
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116730:8"/> composed of watry substance, the reason why, sometimes they are called watry Suns. <hi>Galileus</hi> is of a quite contrary opinion; for, saith he, <hi>Fiunt Parelii in rarioribus nubibus, quae in aëre reperiri possunt, &amp; prorsus siccis omnique humore carentibus, quae vè sunt potius caligines: Parelii</hi> are formed of more rare clouds then usually are found in the ayre, and they altogether drye, and wanting all humour, and these are rather darknesses.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aristotle</hi> generally in his Writings was of this opinion, that the matter of these <hi>Parelii</hi> was derived or begot from the same causes which produce the <hi>Rainbow,</hi> and the <hi>Crown,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from the same materiall cause; for although the matter be a vapour, yet is it not of a watry substance, it comes neerer to the condition of ayre, so much as it may be termed ayre; for if the matter were a dewy cloud, distilling into small drops, it would much differ from that equality, which is wholly neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary, that it might represent the image of the Sun, as of a perfect mirrour. As the <hi>Ancients</hi> have nothing conformed in judgement concerning the matter whereof the <hi>Parelii</hi> are framed, so neither about their form or production; onely they say, they alwayes appear in form of a Sun, and that the Sun is the efficient cause of the production of one <hi>Parelium;</hi> but when the <hi>Parelium</hi> is du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicated, the second may be caused by the first: Yet <hi>Paracelsus</hi> saith, <hi>Defectus roris occasio est &amp; generatio alterius Solis;</hi> the defect of dew is the occasion and generation of another Sun.</p>
            <p>Usually there appears but two <hi>Parelii,</hi> though <hi>Seneca</hi> saith, <hi>Quid impedit, quo minus tot sint, quot nubes fuerunt aptae ad exbiben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam effigiem Solis, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Ancients</hi> have sometimes made mention of three <hi>Parelii,</hi> but rarely of more then two; <hi>Augustine</hi> writes of two seen before the birth of Christ; <hi>Zonoras</hi> in <hi>Vitellio,</hi> mentions two seen after the death of Christ; <hi>Palmerius</hi> speaks of three <hi>Parelii</hi> seen 1466. <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> mentions the sight of three Suns seen at <hi>Wittenberg</hi> 1514. in every of which Suns stood a bloody Sword; the <hi>Tigurines</hi> saw in their Country three Suns, 1528. <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omundus</hi> mentions three Suns in 1619. <hi>Cardan</hi> relates a memorable story of three Suns seen at <hi>Venice</hi> 1532. as any may read in <hi>lib.</hi> 14. <hi>de varietate, cap.</hi> 70.</p>
            <p>They are more frequently seen in the N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rthern Climates, <hi>Quasi rigentibus tis locis, qui Solis vim tam tenuiter excipiunt, condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicatis
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116730:9"/> quandoque Solibus natura consulere satagat:</hi> Another reason is also given, <hi>Quia apud nos, proprium Pareliorum tempus est matuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, cum Sol prope Horizontem versatur, at ibi perpetuo Sol prope Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizontem decurrit.</hi> The proper time of the appearance of <hi>Parelii</hi> in our Northern Countries is matutine, or in the morning, when as the Sun is not far distant from our <hi>Horizon,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Their motion is alwayes with the Sun, nor are they ever far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the Sun then where they were at their first appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; they have no heat, are pale, wan or dull, and their beams look as it were of an <hi>icey</hi> colour; their continuance is but short, sometimes they are visible half an hour, sometimes more, seldom longer then one hour, or one hour and a quarter.</p>
            <p>As I have informed you of the great difference in judgement upon <hi>Parelii,</hi> by the <hi>Ancients,</hi> concerning the matter they are procreated of, so is there also as much disagreement concerning their signification: Some say, <hi>Ab accidentalibus Solibus, frigor a potius &amp; pluvias, quam aestus &amp; incendia expectamus.</hi> Let us expect from accidentall Suns rather colds and rains, then heat or lightning: they more certainly promise rain, and more assured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then the rods or streaks in the clouds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theophrastus</hi> saith in his Booke of the signes of Raine, <hi>Si duo sint Parelii, &amp; simul coronae, celebrem imbrem esse expectandum.</hi> When two Parelii appeare and also Crownes, expect a lusty showre to follow. <hi>Ptolomeus</hi> gives his judgement, <hi>Cum Sol solares nubes, quae Parelia dicuntar, una parte informarit, nubiumque figuras subru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bras, radiosque in longum tendentes circum se habuerit, vehementes fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus significantur pro illis angulis, quos respererint visa illa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aratus</hi> saith no more of <hi>Parelii</hi> then thus, <hi>Duplicem parelium tempestatem praedicere:</hi> a two-fold Mock-sun predicts a tempest, &amp;c. What weather followed these Parelii here in <hi>England</hi> I shall insert in the Conclusions.</p>
            <p>But that these shall have any other signification or portent then upon the Weather, its denyed very stifly and by men ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry learned, yet the event hath ever deluded their judgements: For <hi>Cardanus</hi> long since affirmed, <hi>Tres Soles triumviratus esse sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, &amp; suo tempore significasse imperia Caroli quinti Cesaris, Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rici secundi Gallorum Regis, &amp; Solymani Turcarum Sultani, viz.</hi> Three Sunnes are the signes, or signifie honour to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred on three, or many deserving men; and those seene
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116730:9"/> in his time did signifie the Empire of <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, and of <hi>Henry</hi> the second King of <hi>France,</hi> and of <hi>Solyman Sultan,</hi> or Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of the <hi>Turkes;</hi> and happily they might be signified here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, being they were men in their times of most admirable parts and actions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cornelius Gemma lih.</hi> 1. <hi>Cosino, cap.</hi> 8. <hi>Nec unquam spectari solent ejusmodi, quin nova federa censeantur aut conspirationes clandestinae, ut quem piam fastigio suo dejiciant vel dolo, vel vi, vel malis Artibus compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendant.</hi> Such like Parelii or Mock suns are never visible, but new Leagues are taxed or called in question, or clandestine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracies practised, that so they may overthrow any by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, fraud, deceite or treachery, or entangle men by sinister snares and temptations. That such things have happened in <hi>England</hi> since this appearance, I sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll now make it appeare; for immediately after the apparition of these Parelii, I now treat of, many of the <hi>Scots</hi> Parliament most dishonourably challenge our Parliament with breach of Covenant, which onely them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves most wickedly and notoriously both formerly and then had wrested, broke, and perfideously interpreted according to <hi>Scottish</hi> faith against us, and then most cunningly insinuate with <hi>Langdale,</hi> an <hi>English</hi> fugitive, to surprize <hi>Berwick,</hi> and surren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, when time served, unto them, and for their use, which he in <hi>July</hi> 1648. did, they entertaining him many moneths, and his desperate attendants, at their own <hi>charges,</hi> and in their Kingdom, untill he could effect his <hi>Designe,</hi> sleighting our <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners</hi> (men equall in <hi>valour</hi> and <hi>worth</hi> to the best of the <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tish Nation.</hi>) Then also, or neer that time, did their <hi>Commissioners</hi> or <hi>Agents</hi> sneakingly insinuate into the heads of some malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and malecontented Parties in <hi>London,</hi> matters and things against the honour and esteem of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and of some famous <hi>Members</hi> thereof, traducing our present <hi>Army</hi> with <hi>Schisme,</hi> and their prime <hi>Officers</hi> of <hi>Heresie;</hi> gallant men, whose faces they durst not behold but with <hi>brazen</hi> words: and all this they acted privately and sparingly with glavering pretences, and insinuating words, intentionally to further their own <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs,</hi> which was no more, then to <hi>beget</hi> for themselves a good <hi>belief</hi> from the people, that they intended his <hi>Majesties restorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> to former honour, to settle this Kingdom in its <hi>pristine glory,</hi> and <hi>London</hi> in her <hi>assured Priviledges;</hi> all which was really pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116730:10"/> but <hi>fraudulently</hi> intended according to the <hi>Scottish faith</hi> of this wicked <hi>Army</hi> and its <hi>adherents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How much they, I mean the <hi>Scots,</hi> engaged in this invading <hi>Army,</hi> intend his <hi>Majesties good,</hi> its apparent from their first <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt</hi> 1639. wherein some now engaged are known then to be chief <hi>actors</hi> against his <hi>Majesty;</hi> they having by their <hi>example</hi> not onely encouraged, but led us on to this very height of <hi>fury</hi> wherein now we are; and when we by the necessity of time, and strange fate of <hi>Providence,</hi> were not in a full capacity to cope with his <hi>Majesty</hi> and Northern Forces, many of those very men for our <hi>Goods</hi> assisted us, untill such time as we had gathered <hi>strength</hi> to subsist of our selves, and untill God blessed us with such a <hi>General, viz.</hi> the <hi>Lord Fairfax,</hi> and such gallant <hi>Officers,</hi> and so resolute an <hi>Army,</hi> as, excepting their taking of <hi>New-castle,</hi> and the assistance of some of their large <hi>Army</hi> (for part run away at <hi>Marston Moor</hi>) they did us little service in two yeers time, but like ravenous creatures, devoured all under their commands; yet we paid well and dearly for their <hi>assistance,</hi> and let them depart with more money then all <hi>Scotland</hi> was worth; I wish we had no cause now to question these things, or to look into many of their former actions, but that we might have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained friends as formerly; but sith that people (I still mean the impudent <hi>Contrivers</hi> and <hi>Countenancers</hi> of this scabby <hi>Army</hi>) have violated both <hi>League, Covenant</hi> and <hi>Faith,</hi> and in pursuance of their <hi>malice,</hi> have not blushed to stain our Parliaments ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and our prosperous <hi>Army</hi> with words and terms, unbefit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting so poor a people as themselves, unto their superiours in blood and vertue: I can be no longer their friend as formerly, or will I spare them in discovering their infidelity, untill they have assumed their former honesty, faith and Religion; yet I do and will ever honour those vertuous men of that <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> who did and do stand for a <hi>Pacification</hi> betwixt both <hi>Nations</hi> without bloodshed, and were willing to have composed our differences without an <hi>Army;</hi> and therefore what language I render now, or hereafter shall do, contrary to my former <hi>Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings</hi> in their honour, let all men understand to be spok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n of these despicable fellowes that have marched into <hi>England,</hi> under the conduct of <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>milton,</hi> his Majesties worst enemy, and one of a <hi>Rupertine</hi> fate. Of whom hereafter.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:116730:10"/>
            <p>I mention not their colloguing and glosing with some male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volent Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> in hope they would have assisted them with <hi>Arms, Ammunitions</hi> and <hi>Moneys,</hi> the onely ends for which the rich Citizens were courted and glavered withall, by which their smooth language and continuall vituperating our Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and scandalizing his Excellency the Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant generall <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and the principall <hi>Officers</hi> of the <hi>Army</hi> with opprobrious words and language, and the whole <hi>Army</hi> it self with the terms and notion of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>factious schismaticall crew of Hereticks, Sectaries</hi> and <hi>Anabaptists;</hi> and by which means and their many deceits, these ungracious <hi>Scots Agents</hi> did of late, and still do much mischief to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> great dishonour to the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> and disservice to his <hi>Majesty,</hi> of whom they but for private ends make very small account, so that at last, they onely have brought this whole Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> into a new <hi>Laborinth</hi> of trouble, purposely that themselves migh fish in troubled wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and while we are composing our own differences, them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, like idle <hi>Lurdanes,</hi> might eat the fat of our Country, tax the <hi>Natives</hi> with burdens more heavy then <hi>Aegiptian</hi> Brick-bats,<note place="margin">They perform these acts now in <hi>Lancashire.</hi>
               </note> abuse their wives and children, purloin and steal away their Cattel and houshold-stuffe, or whatsoever their theevish hands could lay hold on, &amp;c. Such things as these I write have been the aime and actions of these unthankfull <hi>Scots,</hi> and have been suddenly subsequent after the appearance of the three <hi>Suns;</hi> so that here is clandestine <hi>Conspiracies</hi> and breach of <hi>League;</hi> as also, in <hi>March</hi> 1647/8. the revolt of Colonel <hi>Poyer</hi> succeeded in <hi>Wales,</hi> in <hi>May</hi> that violent commotion in <hi>Kent</hi> by <hi>Goring</hi> and others; then also, the revolt of some traiterous <hi>Sea-men</hi> the same moneth, from the commands of <hi>Parliament;</hi> after which in <hi>July</hi> the foolish, chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dish <hi>enterprise</hi> of <hi>Buckingham</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> in <hi>Surrey</hi> followed; and lastly, the entrance of the <hi>Scottish</hi> monsters into <hi>Cumberland, July</hi> 7. 1648. which added fuell and furtherance to the great misunderstanding of the <hi>City</hi> unto the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and extream malice of the <hi>Citizens</hi> to the <hi>Army,</hi> but for what cause, neither the wisest man, or most malicious amongst them, can tell: These things I write for instruction and information of <hi>Posterity</hi> hereaft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, and of the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> at present. But to proceed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cornelius Gemma,</hi> or some other <hi>Author</hi> I now remember not,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116730:11"/> saith, presently upon the appearance of six <hi>Suns, Franciscus Galliae Rex in potestatem Hispanorum venerit. Francis</hi> King of <hi>France</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Prisoner to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> &amp;c. At which <hi>Franciscus Resta</hi> makes himself merry, with this conclusion, <hi>Quasi nimirum cum ficti Soles velut Satellites verum Solem cingunt tunc in captivitatem ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant summi Reges:</hi> as if (quoth he) when mock Suns like <hi>Yeomen of the Guard,</hi> do encompasse the true Sun, then our chiefest <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> should fall into captivity▪ Although this was delivered by <hi>Resta</hi> in jest, yet it many times proves true in good earnest, and we know since that time his <hi>Majesty</hi> hath been more narrowly lookt unto in the Isle of <hi>Wight</hi> then formerly, &amp;c. I am much satisfied with that of <hi>Paulus Minerva,</hi> lib. 2. cap. 19. <hi>Parelius aquas aut ventos promittit:</hi> A mock Sun promises waters, showrs or windes; but afterwards, <hi>Alii habent Parelios semper aliquid sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificare singulare coelitus, quod certe intelligendum est cum fiunt crebrio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res; viz.</hi> others will have it, That <hi>Parelii</hi> or mock Suns do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes signifie some singular matter from heaven, which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly is true, when these Apparitions are often times vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible.</p>
            <p>Verily we have had many <hi>Parelii</hi> and <hi>Paraselenae</hi> seen in <hi>England</hi> within this four yeers, and some other prodigious apparitions besides; all which can be no lesse then the undoubted <hi>forerunners</hi> of some more then usuall <hi>accident</hi> or miraculous <hi>Catastrophe</hi> at hand within this our Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and which as yet is not in <hi>esse,</hi> fulfilled, but in <hi>posse,</hi> to be expected; so that I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with Saint <hi>Augustine, Propter haec, novi Solis apparitiones pro miraculosis recognosco:</hi> I do account the apparitions of a new and strange <hi>Sun</hi> for a miracle, and not to be accepted as any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresse, or procreation from <hi>nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paracelsus,</hi> lib. 8. pag. 66. delivers his opinion of these <hi>Parelii</hi> thus, <hi>Hi statum mundi sibi subjecti indicant, non in futurum, sed de die presenter; indicant autem schismata &amp; similia, resque admirandas &amp; raro fieri Solitas; precipuè autem evidentia deliria indicantur, &amp; cona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus stulti superiorum, itaque sicut duos tresve Soles existere superfluum est, ita superfluum est quod illi indicant, &amp;c.</hi> These <hi>Parelii</hi> intimate the state of the world subject unto them, not what shall long after succeed, but from the day presently; they foreshew <hi>schisms,</hi> &amp;c. wonderfull matters, and such as are seldom used to be done; they demonstrate especially evident <hi>madnesse,</hi> and the <hi>foolish en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:116730:11"/> of great men; so that as there is no necessity of three <hi>Suns,</hi> no more is there need of such things as they signifie.</p>
            <p>Some say again, That <hi>Parelii praesagia sunt, non genuina naturae crescentia;</hi> they foretell of some matters and Consults hatching against nature. <hi>Diversa Parelia Regni ejusdem gubernatores fere di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versos aut viros fere principes representant, circulus autem Regni partes aut Civitates, verus ille Sol circuli medio personam Regiam apta simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine monstrat.</hi> Gem. 167. lib. 2. Divers, or many <hi>Parelii</hi> repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent the Governours of the same Kingdom to be many, or it personates men of equall rank, or like <hi>Princes;</hi> the <hi>circle</hi> about the Suns, shew the parts or Cities of that Kingdom; the true Sun in the middle of the circle, declares, by an apt comparison, a Regall person of the same Kingdom.</p>
            <p>I shall willingly conclude with that of <hi>Wolfgangus Meurer,</hi> who having at large discoursed upon the naturall cause of <hi>Pare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lii</hi> and <hi>Paraselenaes,</hi> at last tels us, <hi>sed preter hanc Physicam significati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem, sunt etiam duae aliae, quarum unam Politicam, alteram Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam nominare licebit:</hi> Besides these Physicall or Phylosophicall significations, there are two others, whereof we may term the one <hi>Politicall,</hi> the other <hi>Ecclesiasticall:</hi> In short, he concludes, that the appearance of <hi>Parelii, sunt monitores de insidiis &amp; Consiliis cland<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinis, quae ineuntur adversus eos qui in magno splendore dignitatis rerum potiuntur.</hi> They admonish such as have the government of the Common-wealth, of trechery, cunning &amp; clandesting plottings against them, &amp;c. And of this as an everlasting truth, our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Parliament, who at present govern the great affairs of this Common-wealth, have had lamentable experience, by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt of so many Counties, Ships, Castles and Men from them (yea, of those formerly most faithfull unto them) as also, the ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enations of many of the Citizens of <hi>London</hi> in affection, &amp;c. I shal not urge the <hi>Scottish</hi> defection, which notwithstanding was not publike untill after this prodigious Apparition, as unto matters of Religion, <hi>Plerunque ecclesiae significant sophisticam depravationem purioris doctrinae, &amp; calumnias, quae sparguntur honesto praetextu, varie ad deformandos eos, qui sua virtute &amp; meritis magnum nomen consecuti sunt, ac longè lateque inclaruerunt, &amp;c.</hi> For the most part they sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie a sophisticall depravation of the purer Doctrine, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies spread or divulged abroad under an honest pretence, variously to defame and asperse those, who by their merits and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116730:12"/> vertue have obtained a great name, and been very famous, &amp;c. how true doth this jump with the actions of this Kingdom, our <hi>Army</hi> being composed of more civill and religious men then ever any <hi>Army</hi> was, are nick-named at home, and called <hi>Saints,</hi> and by the <hi>Scots</hi> libellous Paper lately published, they are term<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Sectaries;</hi> those that now continue faithfull to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, let their judgement in <hi>Religion</hi> be what it will, they are termed <hi>Independents</hi> or <hi>Anabaptists;</hi> so that I dare aver, there hath been in no age either such scandals cast upon <hi>Religion</hi> it self, or upon such famous <hi>Commanders</hi> and men as are in our present <hi>Army;</hi> all this <hi>Odium</hi> meerly aspersed upon them, because they are more godly and religious then other men, and who desire the setling hereof in a safe way: what benefit this Kingdom hath received by their means, let some other more able <hi>Pen</hi> commit to <hi>Posterity;</hi> and for our unthankfulnesse to them, let us expect a severe judgement. I now hasten to our <hi>Astrologicall judgement,</hi> framed according to the position of the twelve hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of Heaven, at the three <hi>Suns</hi> first visibility, for it was right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly said of a very learned Philosopher, <hi>Multum in illis praeter nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merum &amp; figuram, ipsa positio Coeli ad praedictionis certitudinem facit, &amp;c.</hi> The positure of Heaven gives much light to a further and more certain prediction, &amp;c. unto which we now hasten.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>astrological chart</figDesc>
               <head>A Scheam Erected att tyme of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> 3 Sunns appearance feb: 28 6<seg rend="sup">h</seg>. 18<seg rend="sup">m</seg> A.M: 1647/8 ad lat: loci: 53: 46</head>
            </figure>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:116730:12"/>
            <p>HEre's a sad and distempered <hi>position</hi> of Heaven, double-bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Signs</hi> culminating and ascending, five <hi>Planets</hi> in opposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to each other; the very time of this <hi>fatall Appearance</hi> it self happening neer unto the time of the <hi>full Moon,</hi> as if the <hi>Planets</hi> and <hi>Stars</hi> of Heaven and the angry <hi>Tutelary Angels</hi> of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom were all swelled with horrour and amazement, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in confusion and disorder, to see this <hi>lamentable</hi> Nation so divided, so betrayed, so bought and sold, and made, as it were, the <hi>Scene</hi> or mark of <hi>villany</hi> and <hi>perjury</hi> by our own selves, our own <hi>Councels</hi> and <hi>Instruments: Qui per Stellas judicare volunt, uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versale equidem judicium convenit judicare, &amp; si particulare, non in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis, sed in magnis rebus in quibus comprehendatur unumquodque univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sale necesse est:</hi> Those who frame predictions according to the course of the Heavens and Planets, it's necessary they give a <hi>generall Judgement;</hi> but if they will give it <hi>particular,</hi> let it not be in <hi>trifles,</hi> or upon unnecessary little matters▪ but in great and weighty affairs, in which it's necessary every universall businesse may be comprehended.</p>
            <p>We will observe this method; and first, endeavour what these <hi>Parelii</hi> may signifie unto his <hi>Majesty:</hi> Secondly, of what concernment they are to the <hi>Parliament</hi> and whole Kingdom, as also, to the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The tenth house shall personate his <hi>Majesty,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sty.</note> the eleventh his <hi>Friends,</hi> from whom any manner of way he may expect assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance: in the tenth it self we finde the <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>agons tayl</hi> locally posi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, running backward, or <hi>against the succession of Signs,</hi> quite through the Sign by a kinde of <hi>retrograde</hi> motion; the cusp of that house is the very degree of <hi>Saturn</hi> his <hi>Aphelium: Cauda Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conis infortunat domum ubi invenitur:</hi> his presence doth alwayes mischief in what house soever you finde him: as here posi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, he infortunates his <hi>Majesty</hi> with reproaches, calumnies, and slanderous aspersions, and were he at <hi>liberty,</hi> it shews or threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens danger to his <hi>Person</hi> by inordinate <hi>Horsmanship,</hi> or some fall from on high, &amp;c. In his <hi>affairs</hi> at present, it either retards them▪ or blasts them with <hi>mistakes</hi> and <hi>misunderstandings, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Aphelium</hi> of <hi>Saturn</hi> moves slowly, not two minutes in a yeer, so shall his <hi>Occasions</hi> go on with great dulnesse and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ergi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion, with many backslidings and oppositions, they shall meet and encounter strong and strange <hi>Adversaries,</hi> much tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116730:13"/> and treacherous <hi>Agents, &amp;c.</hi> The Lord of the tenth house is <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and he <hi>retrograde,</hi> and in his <hi>detriment,</hi> and <hi>cadent</hi> (as from the tenth) from hence is discovered the uncertain state and condition of his <hi>Majesty,</hi> both in his <hi>Affairs</hi> and <hi>Person</hi> at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, <hi>viz.</hi> from hence is deduced a manifestation of turbulen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, tumultuousnesse, and imbecility in prosecution of his <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs;</hi> as also, an absolute improbability of perfecting any honouhable <hi>design</hi> for advancement of his <hi>Majesty,</hi> during the effects and influence of this malevolent <hi>Prodigie,</hi> which indeed is the forerunner neither of restitution in glory to his <hi>Majesty,</hi> or any quietnesse to <hi>Parliament</hi> or the <hi>Kingdom</hi> in generall.</p>
            <p>For more full manifestation hereof, let us behold the face of heaven the <hi>new Moon</hi> preceding this <hi>Apparition,</hi> and therein you finde both <hi>Sol</hi> and <hi>Luna</hi> applying to <hi>Jupiter</hi> his <hi>Majesties Signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator, Jupiter</hi> also then <hi>retrograde, cadent</hi> and <hi>subterranean,</hi> apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to an <hi>opposition</hi> both of <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Mercury,</hi> Planets neither naturally beneficall, or in that <hi>Scheam</hi> potent by scituation in House, or <hi>essentially</hi> well dignified: from hence then we <hi>naturally</hi> and <hi>Astrologically</hi> predict, that these <hi>Parelii</hi> are not the swift <hi>mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sengers</hi> of his <hi>Majesties</hi> wished for <hi>restauration</hi> to his <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>pristine Dignity,</hi> either by violent <hi>Tumults,</hi> sudden <hi>Treaties,</hi> or unnaturall <hi>Wars,</hi> fine <hi>Policies,</hi> or diss<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mbling <hi>Trecheries:</hi> A just dimension of time for his <hi>re-setling,</hi> from hence cannot be col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected; hereby <hi>endeavours,</hi> but not <hi>performances</hi> are manifested.</p>
            <p>These <hi>aseriall</hi> and spirituall, or prodigious <hi>disturbances</hi> neer our earthly <hi>Regions,</hi> do admonish us of most wonderfull <hi>muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> and <hi>catastraphes</hi> in our own <hi>English</hi> Common-wealth, both in the mindes and inclinations of <hi>men;</hi> as also, in the affairs and transactions which are at present, or hereafter may be of and concerning his <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sty,</hi> and between <hi>him</hi> and the serious <hi>Debates</hi> on both sides, <hi>viz.</hi> betwixt <hi>Him</hi> and his <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in very deed, considering the intricate <hi>Laborinths, dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, losses, crosses, vexations, sufferings, scandals, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sertions, miseries, revoltings,</hi> and what not, which I saw these <hi>Parelii</hi> did manifest unto our <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Kingdom;</hi> and the little diminitive <hi>por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> or assurance of <hi>comfort</hi> they afforded unto his <hi>Majesties Friends,</hi> I purposely retarded even to this day my <hi>Astrologicall Judgement</hi> hereupon: But by <hi>divine impulsion,</hi> and the restlesse <hi>provocations</hi> of my publike <hi>Genius,</hi> stirred up by the <hi>malignant
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:116730:13"/> lyes</hi> of my <hi>Mercurian</hi> enemies, I do now again in a sad time <hi>appear,</hi> and am the gratefull <hi>messenger</hi> of comfort and consolation after a few sufferings, unto those who have stood, and still continue fast friends unto the <hi>Parliament;</hi> but am the dolefull <hi>Oracle</hi> of lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and sadnesse to all those that obstinately stand disaffected to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and again shall the second time rise up in <hi>Arms</hi> against the Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>For if we with a serious <hi>consideration</hi> shall but observe that both <hi>Jupiter</hi> is retrograde being Lord of the tenth, and also that <hi>Cauda</hi> is in the tenth house, it might give our <hi>Nobility</hi> a smart and signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant <hi>adviso,</hi> how and in what manner they ought to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>have them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, lest they finde these subsequent words verified on their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons and fortunes in good earnest, viz. <hi>Cauda in decima significat d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectionem Nobilium &amp; Magnatum, atque ipsorum malum esse, &amp; exaltatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem vilium atque ignobilium, &amp;c.</hi> in plain terms, here is imported, That the <hi>Commonalty</hi> shall get the upper hand of the <hi>Nobility,</hi> &amp;c. which must be understood after this manner, that many of them shall do such dishonourable <hi>acts,</hi> and commit such wilfull <hi>follies,</hi> and so grievously oppresse the people, that they <hi>enraged</hi> thereat, shall either quite extinguish, or take all power and command from very many of them, formerly in great <hi>authority,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Fiat voluntas Dei;</hi> God's will be done; and so it is when <hi>justice</hi> is administred equally, as well upon the <hi>Noble</hi> as the <hi>vulgar</hi> persons. But to our former intentions concerning his <hi>Majesty,</hi> we do conj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cture, that as <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> in <hi>August</hi> and <hi>September</hi> come severall times to <hi>conjunction;</hi> sometimes <hi>Mercury</hi> being direct, sometimes retro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade; as also, because <hi>Sol</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> and <hi>Sol</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> comes then to severall <hi>conjunctions;</hi> so I say, we desire and conceive, that about or neer the moneth of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember,</hi> such things as we pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dicted in our <hi>Anglicus</hi> 1648. may come to passe, which we hope may either be a <hi>Personall Treaty</hi> (as we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire) or else very honourable <hi>Proposals</hi> sent unto him, as the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cursors</hi> of more good to follow by this <hi>Parliament,</hi> much conducing to the welfare of his <hi>Majesty,</hi> and safety of the whole Kingdom: if the unlucky coming in of the malignant, dissenting <hi>Scottish</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my from the more honest and modest opinions of the good peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Party in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and an unquiet giddy people of our own, cause no retarding or diversion of our then <hi>Consultations,</hi> to some other very materiall and necessary consideration, for the present defending and strengthning of this Common-wealth against <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:116730:14"/> forces, and <hi>homebred</hi> enemies: for much about those moneths the times seem generally troublesome, and the people full of <hi>fears:</hi> I pray God his <hi>Majesty</hi> stand not then too much upon <hi>puncto's</hi> of honour, and hopes of our <hi>breaches;</hi> and I also wish safe and sure <hi>Propositions</hi> may proceed from the <hi>Parliament,</hi> for the good of us all, that so afterward there may be no starting holes left, either for <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let us now close home to our <hi>English Parliament,</hi> and tell the <hi>Grandees</hi> thereof, the language of heaven, and the portent of this present <hi>Appearance,</hi> in as plain and familiar a <hi>Dialect</hi> of truth, as we may, for it's neither our manner to flatter them, or to delude the expectation of so many thousands as must be eye witnesses of our prediction; some whereof would happily carp and fish out matter for our <hi>dispraise,</hi> if we estrange our <hi>predictions</hi> from the very naturall edicts of the <hi>Stars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pisces</hi> the house of <hi>Jupiter</hi> is their ascendant, and so also <hi>Sagit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary</hi> of his <hi>Majesty,</hi> (God grant we have fair dealing, for this argues both <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> will pretend well:) both the Signs are <hi>Bycorporeall,</hi> or double-bodied; this imports <hi>relapses</hi> on both sides; the Planet <hi>Jupiter</hi> is Lord both of the <hi>Kings</hi> ascendant, and our <hi>Parliaments,</hi> and he <hi>retrograde;</hi> I doubt the actions on both sides will be much questioned by <hi>Posterity,</hi> and that neither of them in the end shall have cause of rejoycing; it's an ill winde blows no body profit: and this is a sad <hi>prodigie</hi> which threatens both Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which neither restores <hi>King</hi> CHARLES to his Crown, or gives assured quietnesse to the <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> thereby. The many and tedious difficulties this present <hi>Parliament</hi> have already from the day of this <hi>Apparition</hi> undergone, and are to run through, are most evidently demonstrated by the <hi>Moon</hi> her opposi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion to the <hi>Sun,</hi> which cleerly shewes vulgar conflicts: and seeing also both Planets, <hi>viz. Sol</hi> and <hi>Luna</hi> well fortified in <hi>angles;</hi> from hence I did fear the revolt and defection of a great part of the Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty of <hi>England</hi> from the Parliament: <hi>Quando Luna continuatur cum Planetis, significat quod est futurum,</hi> Bethen Aph. 34. <hi>viz.</hi> the mischief will continue, because the <hi>Moon</hi> applies to <hi>opposition</hi> of the <hi>Sun:</hi> for the <hi>Moon</hi> in this manner of judicature, represents the <hi>Vulgar.</hi> And if we will know how long this fury or madnesse of theirs shall be permanent, active, and impetuous, we do finde that it may be somewhat lesse then one yeer, and some three moneths; after which time the people shall sensibly perceive their errours, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:116730:14"/> curse the occasioners of their misunderstandings, for they are, and have been undone and abused, severall manner of wayes signified in this <hi>Scheam</hi> of heaven: so also, this Parliament hath suffered, and lost their <hi>estimation</hi> with the people by other wayes: for you must know, the <hi>Moon</hi> in this positure separated from an <hi>oppositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of <hi>Mars,</hi> then of <hi>Mercury;</hi> Pamphlets, Misconceptions of the <hi>Parliaments</hi> intentions, Religious things or men, we call them <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines,</hi> some say <hi>Ministers,</hi> Reports, Ordinances, Calumnies, Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Petitions, &amp;c. have occasionally already, and shall for the future prejudice the <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>lustre</hi> of both houses: and foras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as the <hi>Moon</hi> did also separate from the <hi>opposition</hi> of <hi>Mars,</hi> and he hath much dominion in the ascendant, it points out, and speaks out so much <hi>English,</hi> that the personall corruption and failings of many <hi>Members</hi> entrusted by this Kingdom amongst them, have, I say, begot an <hi>Odium</hi> upon the <hi>Parliament</hi> it self, and the rest of those honourable <hi>Memhers,</hi> who of themselves naturally are of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrpupt judgement, and of pure <hi>English</hi> spirits; and these purer souls, or more generous and <hi>self-denying</hi> spirits, are here signified by the <hi>Sun,</hi> shall in good time rectifie the unbeleeving peoples <hi>fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> and execute such justice amongst themselves, as doubtlesse God will be pleased therewith, and the whole <hi>Kingdom</hi> plentifully satisfied: and although <hi>Sol</hi> may be vitiated by <hi>Mars,</hi> yet <hi>Hermes,</hi> Apho. 65. saith he is lesse hurtfull: <hi>Existentibus Planetis sub radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is, cum infra</hi> 12. <hi>gradus Soli proximi fuerint, infortunantur:</hi> a Planet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Sun beams</hi> is unfortunate, therefore <hi>Mars</hi> cannot hurt the <hi>Sun,</hi> or War much prejudice the <hi>Parliament:</hi> yet this of necessity will follow, either an amendment and compliance of the <hi>Members</hi> themselves, or a finall revolt of the people from them, and so a miserable subversion of the <hi>fundamentals</hi> of this Common-wealth; which although it be greedily thirsted after by many, and such an appearance may be; yet shall not their eyes see it, who most long after it: for the position of <hi>Sol</hi> in the ascendant, pre-signifies that a divine <hi>providence</hi> from heaven will miraculously disperse these corrupt humours in the <hi>Parliament-men</hi> themselves, &amp; actions now so offensive, and give them new and more divine souls then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, whereby they will with cheerfulnesse put in present execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution what may speedily conduce to the good of the whole <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I must confesse, the positure of <hi>Saturn</hi> in the second, doth mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest not onely their want of <hi>Treasure,</hi> but some losse of what for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:116730:15"/> was theirs, whether it be <hi>Ammunition, Castles, Towns</hi> or <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> &amp;c. nor shall they but with much sorrow, expence of time, and great labour regain their losses; but assuredly they shall in the end once more obtain and enjoy what by treachery or folly may be withdrawn from them, and appear in a good <hi>condition,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding all opposition whatsoever.</p>
            <p>Again, the <hi>Sun</hi> amongst the Planets represents <hi>Kings, Emperours, Princes</hi> and <hi>Magistrates,</hi> the <hi>Nobility,</hi> &amp;c. Mock Suns signifies vulgar men: As the true <hi>Sun</hi> here was invironed by two counterfeits, so shall our <hi>Parliament,</hi> and their actions and honour, be shrewdly for a time shaken from the <hi>South,</hi> and from the <hi>Northeast,</hi> and from the <hi>Southwest</hi> and <hi>east:</hi> for at the present appearance of these <hi>Parelii</hi> there was no visible face of <hi>authority</hi> but what was in them, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they shall be the more sensible of the many and infinite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracies, treacheries, and misdemeanours, intended to subvert their lawfull <hi>authority,</hi> many new Leagues, Councels, and secret practises shall be invented and contracted against them, purposely to alter and change, or subvert the <hi>Fabrick</hi> of this Common-wealth, and to dissolve their power to nothing, and as it was said to the <hi>Jew, Perditio tua ex te;</hi> so is your own destruction contrived amongst your selves; else, what doth <hi>Mercury</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> in your ascendant? which doth evidently point out some wicked <hi>Vipers</hi> amongst your selves, who sit and consult to betray us; which God in his mercy will in due time discover.</p>
            <p>And although the vigorous <hi>influence</hi> of this <hi>Prodigie</hi> shall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly stumble even the <hi>resolutions</hi> of the most assured <hi>Patriots</hi> of this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> by reason of the many sudden alterations of the people, and the multitude of trecheries daily arising, which they shall discover in their former friends, yet let no mans <hi>heart</hi> fail him; for after a long <hi>series</hi> of disturbance, Victory and conquest Peace and quietnesse, shall and will follow the <hi>Parliament</hi> and their <hi>Armies: In ea parte in qua Sol &amp; Luna fortunabuntur erit victoria;</hi> in that part of heaven where you finde the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon</hi> fortunated, there expect Victory: The <hi>Sun</hi> is in our <hi>Parliaments</hi> ascendant, so is <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Mercury;</hi> if the <hi>Sun</hi> be our friend, and <hi>Mars,</hi> as they are, we little fear the other Planets: and let those who rise, or intend to disturb our <hi>Parliament,</hi> remember this <hi>Aphorism, Oportet maximum impedimentum esse rerum quae sunt in potestate signi in quo fuerit Planeta ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, vel retrogradus aut in malo esse Solis,</hi> Almanso 112. <hi>Mercury</hi> is here the Parliaments enemy, disposed by us in our ascendant, not in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:116730:15"/> the tenth; <hi>Mars</hi> afflicts him, he is <hi>combust,</hi> besieged, what not: let our rambling <hi>prophets</hi> interpret his further signification to all such as rebelliously shall shew their <hi>teeth</hi> against the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and let not the Citizens of <hi>London</hi> be too confident, for they are to be <hi>invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly</hi> led into errours, if not further mischief; for <hi>Quando Planeta est cum Sole sunt vires ejus debiles, &amp; suum deminuitur judicium;</hi> A Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net with the <hi>Sun</hi> loses his vertue, his influence is weak, and his judgement, or things signified by him are of no force; for even the <hi>Planetary Intelligencees</hi> (if they did raise these two <hi>mock Suns</hi>) have likewise determined by the positure of heaven their <hi>events,</hi> and how it shall chance unto both the <hi>King</hi> and his Party, and to the <hi>Parliament</hi> and their Party, and to the <hi>Kingdom</hi> in generall.</p>
            <p>For more cleer evidence of this <hi>question,</hi> I say, and am hereunto led by former experience and reason, the best and safest guides in <hi>Astrologie,</hi> that as the <hi>Moon,</hi> who signifies our <hi>Parliaments</hi> enemies, doth after her seperation, apply forcibly unto a <hi>trine</hi> of <hi>Saturn,</hi> and he is personally located in their house of Substance, and also because there is <hi>reception</hi> betwixt <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Saturn,</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> and <hi>Sol</hi> both apply to a <hi>sextile</hi> of <hi>Saturn,</hi> no <hi>prohibiton</hi> or <hi>frustration</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervening; and because that <hi>Saturn</hi> is in a fixed Sign, and so also <hi>Venus;</hi> from hence I collect a certain and infallible position ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>naturall causes,</hi> That the Parliament and people of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who are their friends, that have stood, and stand firm unto them, shall recover whatever either the trechery of some, or force of others hath, or shall steal from them, upon any pretence what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever; but all this with great labour, vexation and anxiety: and hereof let the bastard-blew-cap <hi>Scot</hi> (who so basely degenerate from former principles) take notice; I mean those ingratefull <hi>monsters</hi> under the destructive commands of <hi>Hamilton,</hi> their most mischievous <hi>General:</hi> But of his <hi>Rupertine</hi> fate we will speak here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after in a page by it self.</p>
            <p>To conclude therefore at this time, these <hi>mock Suns</hi> are the Messengers of tumults, trecheries, not of very much blooshed, &amp;c. and do rather argue his <hi>Majesty</hi> impeded by his own Friends, and his own Results, then restored; they foreshew many trecherous great ones amongst our <hi>Grandees,</hi> they threaten them with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended mischievous <hi>massacre,</hi> but it will not be performed: The effects of these distempers are like to continue eleven moneths in somewhat a vigorous manner; after which they lessen. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause <hi>Posterity</hi> will more enquire into our <hi>Writings</hi> then this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:116730:16"/> age, I must acquaint them, how that in the figure of heaven upon the apparition of three <hi>Suns</hi> seen <hi>November</hi> 19. 1644. the 26. of <hi>Sagittary</hi> did then ascend; upon those three <hi>Suns</hi> appearance <hi>April</hi> 3. 1647. the 15. of <hi>Sagittary</hi> did then possesse the angle of the seventh house; and now we have the 25. of <hi>Sagittary</hi> culminating, neer the very degree of the ascendant of the last <hi>Conjunction of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> 1642/3. so that we may evidently discover, that the first <hi>mock Suns</hi> in 1644. threatned damage to his <hi>Majesty,</hi> for he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined after that time, and is not yet recovered.</p>
            <p>Immediately after the <hi>mock Suns</hi> apparition in <hi>April</hi> 1647. the Army and Parliament had some sucffling, but since that very day unto this present, they have declined in honour, and the people excited miraclously against them: but after these present <hi>Appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> without doubt the <hi>calamity</hi> will be <hi>universall</hi> both to King, Parliament and People, especially to the Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> for <hi>Mercury</hi> is not onely afflicted of <hi>Mars,</hi> but hastening to <hi>combustion.</hi> But sith there is more to be said of them upon the <hi>Conjunction of Saturn and Mars,</hi> I forbear. A word of the <hi>Clergie</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A great cause of our present <hi>miseries,</hi> and some subsequent, may be feared <hi>Astrologically</hi> to arise from some disaffected <hi>Clergie-men,</hi> or lukewarm <hi>Parliamentary-men,</hi> who are double tongued, &amp; shew their <hi>Janus</hi> faces; sometimes <hi>Regal,</hi> then <hi>Parliamentary,</hi> other times <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified,</hi> then <hi>Neutrals,</hi> whose vagrant <hi>tongues</hi> more poison the people, then all our enemies: but the time is <hi>coming,</hi> when these false <hi>Priests</hi> shall have short <hi>horns;</hi> for <hi>Jupiter</hi> their <hi>Significator</hi> in generall, is here in <hi>Virgine: Planeta in domo inimici sui, est ut vir in domo alterius, inter quos jam advenit odium &amp; ira,</hi> Bethen Apho. 31. A Planet in the house of his enemy, is like one in another mans, betwixt whom there's already some rancour and malice: And in truth we have discovered so much weaknesse in this people we call <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> we now begin to dis-esteem them, and conceive of them as they well deserve, and are not willing to be any more lul'd asleep with their <hi>Canonicall whips, Confessions,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Be it how it will, <hi>Mercury,</hi> another of their <hi>Significators,</hi> is <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bust, Quando Mercurius est cum Sole, sunt vires ejus debilis, &amp; suum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minuitur judicium:</hi> When <hi>Mercury</hi> is with the <hi>Sun,</hi> his vertues are weak, and his judgement of no account: no more after a while will their <hi>peevish invectives.</hi> For it's a just judgement of the alseeing Providence inflicted upon those we call <hi>Divines,</hi> that for many ages have so cunningly steered the greatest Actions of our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:116730:16"/> that now, I say, by their base covetousnesse and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall oppression of the people, they are neither feared of the <hi>poorest,</hi> or beloved of the <hi>middle</hi> sort of people, or in any honour of the <hi>better</hi> sort.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Thus much the Kirk hath got</l>
               <l>To bring her to a wofull Lot.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Yet I wish all prosperity to the well meriting or deserving <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine,</hi> and my self give all respects unto them.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A brief MEMORIAL of such Passages as hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened presently with us in <hi>England,</hi> after the three SUNS appearance.</head>
               <p>IN <hi>March,</hi> a generall murmuring possessed most Counties of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the Commonalty every where began to dislike the actions of the Parliament, and a subtill kinde of people dispersed themselves into most Counties of this Kingdom, to prepare the people to mutiny; the Parliament either not having notice, or willing to be sensible of it.</p>
               <p>About the middle of the moneth, <hi>Ferdinando</hi> Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> in <hi>Yorkeshire</hi> deceased, being the greatest pillar in the North for the Parliament; he dyed full of yeers, more full of honour, having most zealously in this Cause, from the first beginning, served his Country faithfully, and obeyed the commands of Parliament.</p>
               <p>In this Moneth Colonell <hi>Poyer</hi> Governor of <hi>Pembroke</hi>-Castle, and one who had formerly performed excellent service for the Parliament, now revolts and fortifies the Town and Castle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>against them; whom Lievtenant Generall <hi>Cromwell,</hi> with much honor and gallantry surrounded with his Army, and in <hi>July</hi> took both the Town and Castle of <hi>Pembroke,</hi> as also the person of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer.</hi> In this Moneth the <hi>Scottish</hi> Parliament, <hi>viz.</hi> the prevailing Party therein, Voted forty thousand men to invade us for our goods. This is that Parties faithfull keeping the Covenant, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do their <hi>English</hi> friends.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Aprill</hi> Mens minds continued very unsetled, so that upon a slight occasion on Sunday, the ninth of <hi>Aprill,</hi> severall Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices, and others in <hi>London,</hi> made a great Tumult, Marcht through the <hi>Strand</hi> with Colors they had taken from the Train'd Bands, with Swords, Broomstaves, Halberds, inquiring the way to the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:116730:17"/>
                  <hi>Muse,</hi> where Colonell <hi>Rich</hi> his Regiment of Horse then lay; and to <hi>Whitehall,</hi> where a Regiment of Colonell <hi>Baxters</hi> Foot were. Colonell <hi>Rich</hi> his Horse presently appeared, and in an instant, there was neither Colors, Boys or staves to be seen, all dispersing themselves as they might best with safety. The civility of these Troopers, even to these Youths, and to many abusive people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, was very great (as I my selfe saw) who onely desired all of them to repaire to their Houses, and to be quiet, and no hurt should be done them. That night produced a new uprore in the City; so that severall Gates were kept shut by a rude people, and a Magazine in <hi>Leaden-hall</hi> the Munday after, very neer surprized, had not a handfull of his Excellencies Souldiers rescued it, and routed those unquiet people, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The two and twentieth of this Moneth, the Duke of <hi>Yorke</hi> was stolne from St. <hi>James;</hi> and the whole Moneth was generally spent in contriving severall Petitions of strange consequences, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturbe the Parliament: The first whereof was that of <hi>Essex,</hi> and the Common-Counsell were much disturbed about some flying reports, fathered upon the Army; but nothing appeared against the Army upon due examination.</p>
               <p>In <hi>May,</hi> the <hi>Scots</hi> send our Parliament some wrangling Papers, unjustly laying much blame upon us, and justifying their own unworthy actions; but the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dly party of that Nation, and their reverend Divines, put out a Declaration against the War; which was honorably done: After this Moneth, I never in <hi>Anglicus</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the name of <hi>Scot.</hi> The <hi>Surrey</hi> Men present a Petition to both Houses, of ill consequence; their foot Freeholders (who were very unruly, as I saw with my own eyes, both in the <hi>Strand</hi> and in the Hall at <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>stminster</hi>) had some dispute and ill language with Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell <hi>Baxsters</hi> foot, who Guarded the House that day; but the Colonels men, though much provoked, forbore, untill one of their Men was slain by a <hi>Surrey</hi> Broom-man or Miller (a Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder forsooth) but then they cleer'd the Hall, and made the simple men know, that a Souldiers Sword cuts deeper then an ill word. Indeed many of the Foot Petitioners were fellows incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable, and purposely provided to make a Tumult; their Horse in number seven or eight hundred, were very civil, and some Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen there were amongst them.</p>
               <p>This Moneth an unquiet People in <hi>Kent</hi> rise in Armes against the Parliament, keepe their Randezvouz at <hi>Rochester,</hi> others rob
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:116730:17"/> Ships about <hi>Detford,</hi> and keepe Guards there; but these within three dayes of themselves run away: they who rose at <hi>Rochester</hi> were well cudgeld at <hi>Maidston</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> where his Excellency the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> (unto whose valiant atchievements this Kingdome stand perpetually indebted) after an hot and sharp dispute, quite routed, destroyed and tooke prisoners all that there opposed him in <hi>Maidston,</hi> to his own eternall honour, (who deeply him self in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Kent</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered by the Lord <hi>Fairfax.</hi>
                  </note>) and the perpetuall renown of those worthy Soldiers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his then Command. His Excellency having conquered with a handfull of Men, that Province which <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror could not with the same royall Army which obtained for him all <hi>England.</hi> In the third week of this Month, Hailstones were taken up at <hi>Walton</hi> two inches about. The 26. of this Month,<note place="margin">The <hi>Welsh</hi> routed.</note> eight roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Ships desert the Parliament. This Month Colonell <hi>Thornton</hi> routed the <hi>Welch</hi> Forces under <hi>Powell</hi> and <hi>Laughorn,</hi> two valiant men, but, who very unfortunately having served the Parliament, now to their great shame revolt: but heaven hath also delivered these men into our hands again.</p>
               <p>In the moneth of <hi>June</hi> the <hi>Essex</hi> men seemed to rise against the Parliament, a <hi>commo ion</hi> appearng; and it was generally thought they would have joyned with <hi>Goring,</hi> who with a body of Horse got into <hi>Essex</hi> out of <hi>Kent;</hi> him and his Horse his Excellency the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> pursues; the <hi>Essex</hi> men (like wise people) lay down their Arms, and receive an Act of <hi>Indempnity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In or about the first week of <hi>June, Pomfret</hi> Castle was surprized,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Colchester</hi> besieged.</note> and stands out against the Parliament. The thirteenth of this moneth or neer it, his <hi>Excellency</hi> appears before <hi>Colchester,</hi> and with a handfull of men beats the Lord <hi>Goring</hi> and Sir <hi>Charles Lucas</hi> into <hi>Colchester,</hi> where he then began his Siege,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Essex</hi> and <hi>Suffolk</hi> assist the Lord Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall.</note> the <hi>Essex</hi> and <hi>Suffolk</hi> men most honourably, and like themselves, assisting with very nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and valiant Souldiers, both Foot and Horse. Divers Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were again presented to the Parliament this moneth, of seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall natures; some pleasing, others not so. The twenty fourth of this moneth there was much unrulinesse at a Common Hall in <hi>London,</hi> much to the dishonour of the City, and that place, where nothing in former ages or times appeared but <hi>gravity</hi> and <hi>mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>July</hi> the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> old <hi>Holland,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A simple Uproar.</note> and young <hi>Peterbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough,</hi> make a childish uproar, rise against the Parliament, are beaten, killed, taken and routed; a sufficient payment for their
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:116730:18"/> follies, who upon so weak principles intended to raise so mighty a <hi>fabrick.</hi> Prince CHARLES appears at <hi>Yarmouth.</hi> Now comes out a filthy thing called,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Scots</hi> print against the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>
                  <hi>The Scots Declaration,</hi> full of lyes and ill language against the Parliament and Army, penned by the Devil, or one of his Clerks. <hi>Pembroke</hi> Castle, <hi>Poyer, Powell, Laughorn,</hi> are all surrendred to the succesfull <hi>Cromwell.</hi> The <hi>Prince</hi> seizes Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants Ships, demands twenty thousand pound for redemption.</p>
               <p>These few notions I leave to <hi>Posterity,</hi> that they may see what actions immediately succeeded the apparition of the three Suns, it being generally received amongst all that allow of Predictions,<note place="margin">In <hi>August</hi> the <hi>Scots</hi> steal and plunder in <hi>Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire,</hi> wher the three Suns were visible.</note> that they are the Precursors of divisions, clandestine Plots, trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries, breaches of Leagues and Covenants, and sudden Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions against Authority: which whether the preceding discourse in some measure maketh not good, I must leave to future times to judge of.</p>
               <p>Now followes an exact <hi>Diary</hi> of the Winde and Weather, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served and taken by a learned <hi>Esquire</hi> of this Kingdom, unto whose pains and great labour, my self and <hi>Posterity</hi> must stand en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged. His name without commission I dare not mention.</p>
               <div type="weather_report">
                  <p>THe <hi>28.</hi> of <hi>February</hi> there was a frost in the morning, fair and dry all day, but somewhat sharp and cold, the winde good, stiffe in the North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>west, and about seven at night and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>omewhat after, a fall of snow that cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ground, afterward the <hi>Moon</hi> and <hi>Stars</hi> appearing, but a further threat of ill weather (according to common observation, &amp;c.)</p>
                  <p>The <hi>29.</hi> a frost in the morning, the day sometimes stormy, with Snow or Hail, sometimes a hot Sun-shine, the Winde Northerly and good sharp, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>March</hi> the first, <hi>1647/8.</hi> this day sharp and cold, often stormy with Snow and Hail, the Winde Northerly.</p>
                  <p>The second, a great Frost in the morning, the day close, Snowing little or much most part of the day, but misling Weather, the Winde Easterly, and some point in the South, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The third, a very hard Frost in the morning, the day fair and drye, the Winde Easterly, no great Gale, but pretty cool, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The fourth, very Stormy at severall times, both the preceding night, and this instant day, sometimes Snow, sometimes Hail, the Winde all day a high Gale Easterly, and very cold, even freezing where the <hi>Sun</hi> did not extend his heat, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The fifth, a continuation of Frost untill about eight in the forenoon, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward a relaxation, the day being free of any kinde of Storms, and the Winde
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:116730:18"/> still Easterly, (some little point in the North) and pretty cool, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The sixth, dark and close Weather, but very dry, the Winde good high Northerly, and very sharp, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The seventh dry and cold Weather, the Winde North-west, some little Rain betwixt three and five of the clock after noon, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The eighth, slattering, stormy Weather for the most part, and so most part of the foregoing night, the Winde Northeast, and very cold, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The ninth much like to the former day, good store of Rain, especially to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards night, the Winde high and boysterous Northerly, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The tenth, the Winde Westerly, a small Frost in the morning, the rest of the day fine, dry and temperate Weather, untill about five of the clock, after which time some Rain, and a further inclination to it, the Ayre being very much clouded, dropping, and very dark, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The eleventh, cloudy, and many Showrs, especially in the forenoon and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards night, the Winde pretty high in the West, &amp;c. much Rain in the night, and extream temp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>stuous Weather, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The twelfth, the Winde very loud in the North, and cold, most part of the day; after four of the clock fine temperate Weather, all the day dry and cleer, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The thirteenth, the Winde very high and turbulent in the West, very dry and cleer for the most part, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The four<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eenth, the Winde Northwest, pretty high and cool, the day some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times cleer, sometimes cloudy, but very dry, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The fifteenth, the Winde in the West a good strong Gale, but very tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and dry Weather, untill about six in the evening, when there fell some Rain, and the Winde then struck into a point Northerly, very boysterous.</p>
                  <p>The sixteenth, the Winde very loud and boysterous in the Northwest, the day sometimes Stormy with Hail, but the Storms of short continuance, not much wetting, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The seventeenth, a little Frost in the morning, fine dry Weather (and pretty cool) untill about three in the afternoon, the Winde all that time almost due West; afterward the Winde removing somewhat Southerly, a dark and close skie, beginning and inclining to Rain, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The eighteenth, the Winde in the West a good strong Gale, the Weather dry and temperate, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The nineteenth, the Winde Westerly and very dry and temperate Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The twentieth, the temper of the Weather much like the former day, and the Winde Westerly, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>21.</hi> fair, dry and temperate Weather, the Winde moderate in the Southwest, &amp;c.</p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:116730:19"/>
                  <p>The <hi>22.</hi> fair and dry untill about one of the clock after noon; afterward, close, dark Weather, with gentle Rain, and the Winde so calm all day, as scarce to be observed with certainty in what quarter it moved, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>23.</hi> close, dry Weather, and very temperate, the Winde in the West, &amp;c. towards night the Winde chopt into the North, but no whit offensive, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>24.</hi> fine Spring-like Weather, the Winde very calm in the West, &amp;c. In the night the Winde did somewhat rise, and there fell pretty store of Rain.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>25.</hi> the Winde extraordinary strong and boisterous in the West all day, and very cold; some small storms of Hail in the afternoon, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>26.</hi> the Winde Northerly and very cold, the forenoon dry and fair, divers small storms of Hail in the afternoon, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>27.</hi> the Winde Northerly and cold, many small storms of Hail and Snow in the afternoon, the evening calm and bright, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>28.</hi> a great Frost in the morning, from eleven of the clock in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon dark druggie Weather, the Winde high and boysterous in the South, great store of Rain in the evening, and a likelihood of continuance; the Winde high in the night, with some fall of Rain, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>29.</hi> the Winde very high in the Southwest, a great storm of Hail about six at night, afterward very fair and cleer, the Winde still somewhat high, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>30.</hi> day sometimes cleer, sometim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s showring, the Winde Westerly pretty high and cool, but calm towards evening, and a fine cleer night to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>31.</hi> a Frost in the morning, and dry Weather all day, though much cloudy, the Winde pretty strong in the Southwest, &amp;c.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>astrological chart</figDesc>
                     <head>A figure of heauen for the Conjunctōn of ♄ and ♂ ☿ 28<seg rend="sup">o</seg> June 1<seg rend="sup">h</seg> 57′ P:M LONDINVM-ANGLIE</head>
                  </figure>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:116730:19"/>
               <head>An ASTROLOGICAL Judgement up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Conjunction</hi> of SATURN and MARS the two malevolent Planets, <hi>June</hi> 28. 1648.</head>
               <p>GOd almighty, from whose bounty all goodnesse and science proceeds, assisting my willing <hi>Genius,</hi> even in these tumultuous seasons, and in this nick of time when our <hi>Parliament</hi> have so few friends, and is so contemptible, in the squint eyes and depraved judgements both of some Citizens and <hi>Cavaliers</hi> (as that their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent ruine is expected) I will proceed to give an <hi>Astrological</hi> Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon this so formidable <hi>Conjunction of Saturn and Mars,</hi> the onely <hi>Basis</hi> from whence the weekly simple <hi>Mercuries</hi> fetch their lying hodge podge <hi>Oracles,</hi> which have of late so oft deluded the people, and of whose pretty cheats and malicious ignorance, now the whole Kingdom (infected therewith) cannot but be miserably sensible, and their own ingenuous Malignant Party enraged with fury, to see themselves incited and invited to giddy <hi>commotions,</hi> sudden <hi>risings,</hi> and unnaturall <hi>rebellions</hi> against this present <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and their Country, by these so lowsey Prophets, the very scorn of Men and <hi>Schollers</hi> (who ever promise Victory unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves) and whose names if I should mention, though sleightly, it were to them an eternall honour: but I leave them to receive from <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Parliament</hi> just rewards for their many abuses, and will endeavour to support my <hi>Astrologicall</hi> Judgement with strength of reason, according to the naturall grounds of the more pure <hi>Astrologie,</hi> and with the most regular and rationall <hi>Aphorisms</hi> that the reverend <hi>Professors</hi> have left us, offering most willingly a free and quiet <hi>dispute</hi> unto any learned <hi>Astrologian</hi> of <hi>Europe,</hi> if he shall contradict my present Writing; but to our own nationall scam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling fellowes, <hi>viz.</hi> the weekly <hi>Mercuries,</hi> I scorn to take even the least knowledge of the best of them, being meer botching <hi>Scrubs,</hi> fit for nothing but hanging.</p>
               <p>It was well said of <hi>Cardanus</hi> Seg. 3. Apho. 122. <hi>Reconditae rationes rerum docent nos, ut illis credamus;</hi> the abstruse or more mysterious reasons of things teach us, that we credit those reasons: <hi>Qui au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem inter multa falsa, pauca miscet vera, non est in recitando dicta ejus illi quicquam tribuendum: viz.</hi> he who delivers amongst many lyes now and then one truth, to such a one, or unto his Words, Actions or
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:116730:20"/> Writings, we should give no belief. These words pertain to the malignant <hi>Prophets,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The 28. of <hi>June</hi> 1648. is now silently passed over, although predicted so fatall to our <hi>Parliament,</hi> and so destructive to us poor <hi>Roundheads,</hi> that have adventured our Stocks in their bottom: A mad and Gipsie-like <hi>Prophecy</hi> it was, that those effects (how great soever) depending upon the <hi>Conjunction,</hi> should antecede its being, &amp;c. However, that day, and the three last days in <hi>Iune</hi> being the last limited dayes of the present <hi>Parliaments</hi> existence, are passed over, and we see with our eyes that the <hi>Parliament</hi> is not dead; and we heard with our ears that very day no more then a whirling ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant murmuring <hi>rumour</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> that his Excellency the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> was totally defeated before <hi>Colchester,</hi> the Siege raised, the Members of both Houses fled: this is <hi>prophetically</hi> printed, and not yet retracted, though a <hi>Bulling lye,</hi> &amp;c. Oh it is, and must needs be the worst of <hi>Causes</hi> that hath no defence but lyes, calumnies, and personall aspersions, &amp;c. But I am to treat <hi>Astrologically.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Subject-matter<note place="margin">Subject-Matter.</note> is <hi>A conjunction of Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> the two malevolent and worst Planets, whose influence indeed may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce wonderfull alterations and mutations, but not wholly of themselves, without other concomitant causes, preceding and subsequent <hi>configurations;</hi> of which our most precious Adversaries have taken no notice: Oh Parliament forgive them, they know not how to do it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ergo,</hi> omi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous to men and great Cattle.</note>The <hi>conjunction</hi> it self fals to be in the <hi>Asterism</hi> of <hi>Taurus,</hi> now extending it self to the very 25. of <hi>Gemini:</hi> in this circuit of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees we have many fixed <hi>Stars;</hi> some neer the degree of the <hi>conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> it self; as, the <hi>horns of the Bull,</hi> of the nature of <hi>Mars;</hi> so also, the <hi>Buckler,</hi> the <hi>Feet,</hi> and the <hi>left Shoulder</hi> of <hi>Orion,</hi> of the severall natures of <hi>Saturn, Iupiter, Mars</hi> and <hi>Mercury,</hi> which rationally and artificially commixed with the <hi>Erraticals,</hi> do many times pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce <hi>thunder, lightning, fiery apparitions</hi> in the Ayre, thundering and extravagant high conceptions in man. The <hi>conjunction</hi> it self is neer the <hi>Eclipticall line; Mars</hi> having no latitude at all, but verging Northward, his influence therefore the stronger: <hi>Saturn</hi> having one degree <hi>Meridionall,</hi> is posited neer such fixed Stars as are of the nature of <hi>Mercury, Saturn, Mars</hi> and the <hi>Moon:</hi> here is a pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty medley of fixed Stars, concomitant with the Planets: The ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects depending hereupon are like to be various, turbulent, &amp;c. These fixed Stars I do mention, as much conducing to discover
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:116730:20"/> the effects of the <hi>conjunction</hi> it self; for <hi>Rigel,</hi> Apho. 66. invites our consideration hereunto; <hi>non obliviscaris Stellas fixas, &amp; gradus nonae Spherae immobiles, in quibus fiunt eae conjunctiones &amp; quadraturae, virtutes mansionum miscendo:</hi> Forget not the fixed Stars, and the immova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble degrees of the ninth Sphear, in which these <hi>conjunctions</hi> of the Planets, and their <hi>quadrate</hi> aspects are made and posited, commix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing herewith, or with their vertue, the influence of their severall mansions: unto whom consenteth <hi>Dasipodius,</hi> Apho. 9. <hi>Stellarum fixarum opus manifestius est, opere trium superiorum, earum (inquam) quae conspicuae sunt magnitudinis aut saltem mediocris cum parva latitudine, &amp;c.</hi> The operation of the fixed Stars themselves, is more manifested or apparent by the <hi>conjunction</hi> of the superiour Planets with them, with such fixed Stars, I say, which are famous or conspicuous, or but of moderate magnitude having small <hi>latitude</hi> from the <hi>Ecliptick.</hi> The very truth is, that we have this malevolent <hi>conjunction</hi> neer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Oculus Tauri,</hi> a most impetuous and violent fixed Star; if we either beleeve our own experience, or the presages of our Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessours, there did never happen any <hi>Eclips, conjunction,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1603 King <hi>James</hi> came in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o <hi>England.</hi>
                  </note> or <hi>opposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the Superiours neer that part of <hi>Gemini,</hi> but it produced admirable effects: let me go no further then to tell you, that the first <hi>conjunction</hi> of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Iupiter</hi> upon their entrance into the fiery <hi>Trygon,</hi> was in <hi>Sagittary,</hi> 1603. in <hi>opposition</hi> to this almost degree of our <hi>conjunction,</hi> (omitting many other examples,<note place="margin">Fatall to the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard.</hi>
                  </note> we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Eclipse in the 10. of <hi>Gemini,</hi> 1639. and the place of the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon</hi> 1644. <hi>Novemb.</hi> 19. at the appearance of the three <hi>mock Suns,</hi> fatall to the Malignants ever since;) besides, this is not a <hi>conjunction</hi> of the inferiour, but superiour Planets; <hi>Quanto majus sydus est ac motus etiam velocior eo etiam opera syderis sunt manifestiora, &amp;c.</hi> Dasipodius Apho. 8. The greater the Planet is, and the more swift his motion, so much the more manifest shall his effects ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear: Both <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> in our positure are very swift, and do greatly exceed their mean motion; <hi>Saturn</hi> his diurnall motion being six minutes, and <hi>Mars</hi> his 42.</p>
               <p>From hence we may conjecture the actions and designes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending hereupon will be great and eminent, and impetuously,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gemini</hi> a famous Sign.</note> furiously, and with great violence and speed be carried on and be prosecuted; and these suddenly and in a moment after this <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction</hi> it selfe is past. And is the Signe it selfe wherein the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction</hi> is in, is <hi>Aëry,</hi> and famous amongst the twelve Signs of the Zodiacke, by reason of the many noble fixed Stars therein
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:116730:21"/> posited on both sides the Eclipticke, and the now present scituati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of these superiors therein; we cannot from hence expect tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viall Negotiations, or vain fantasticall <hi>Ideas,</hi> but matters of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, consultations to purpose, and those of principall eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and highest concernment of Men in Authority and matters equivolent; for <hi>cum superioribus nunquam judicia, de rebus parvis fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies Rigel. Apho.</hi> 39. When thou shalt judge the effects succeeding a <hi>Conjunction</hi> of the Superiors, expect from thence no small or tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viall matters to succeed. From hence we may derive a candid judgement, of the magnitude and influence this <hi>Conjunction</hi> hath upon the generall Actions of our Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> and the greatest persons therein Inhabiting; and particularly upon the City of <hi>London,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>London</hi> much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction.</note> and their actions and consultations, and upon the Southerne and Westerne parts fron <hi>London</hi> or West of <hi>England;</hi> which for ought I see are to continue many dayes in great vigor and manifold action; for neither of the two Malevolents have any great impediment, but as posited in the eight. <hi>Manent ergo vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes &amp; significata erratieaerum si non combustas &amp; retrogradas has stellas invenies, Rigel. Apho.</hi> 39. The influence of the Planets and matter or vertue of their Significations remaine and continue, when you finde their Significators are neither Combust or Retrograde, &amp;c. Of all these Aphorismes we shall make good use in the ensuing judgement; for in our Scheame we neither have <hi>Mars</hi> or <hi>Saturne</hi> Retrograde, or Combust, but swift, direct and well dignified, essentially, or accidentally. And certainly this very <hi>Conjunction</hi> is the Prodromus of singula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> actions, both in our own Common-wealth, and also in the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland;</hi> for it is an indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitable rule, according to Astrologie: <hi>Deteri orantur genera hominum per transmutationes illarum magnarum Conjunctionum cum succedentes ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micabiliter configurantur cum figuris praeteritarum, unde una rota ascen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt &amp; descendunt, que perpetuo nec uno esse, nec una forma rotantur, Rigel. Apho.</hi> 32. The kinds and qualities of men are depraved, made worse, or corrupted by the transmutation of the great Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, when as those Conjunctions which succeed, are inimica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly configurated with the preceding positures of Heaven, &amp;c. That we make use of this Aphorisme, let us consider that the <hi>Conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> in the eighth degree of <hi>Sagitarius,</hi> which was celebrated <hi>Decem.</hi> 7. 1603. the same yeer when King <hi>James</hi> came into <hi>England;</hi> must be the <hi>Locus à quo,</hi> or the first assured Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain or ground-worke from which, untill the yeer 1801. in an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strologicall
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:116730:21"/> way of judgement, we must more or lesse derive a Conjecture of Humane contingencies in this Kingdome espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, and in <hi>Scotland;</hi> and generally over all <hi>Europe:</hi> we must also commix therewith the two later <hi>Conjunctions</hi> of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter,</hi> one in 1623. and the other in 1642/3. and we know that in 1603. the <hi>English</hi> Monarchy was divolved to the <hi>Scottish</hi> race,<note place="margin">A great Plague at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended King <hi>James</hi> his coming into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> 1603 And a greater Plague followed his death.</note> to the exceeding benefit of that Nation, and the enriching of them that came in amongst us, but to the impoverishing of the <hi>English;</hi> multitudes of that people since having obtained vast Estates, and great Offices of trust and profit in our Kingdome; of all which they have ever known how to make the best use. In that <hi>Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> we have <hi>Gemini</hi> the Cusp of the seventh and <hi>Luna</hi> in the tenth degree, and 52. minutes; as if the vulgar did not much care for the <hi>Scots</hi> company.</p>
               <p>In the positure of heaven 1623. <hi>July</hi> the seventh, upon the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Conjunction</hi> of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> in 6. 45. <hi>Leo</hi> the very tenth degr. of <hi>Gemini</hi> was the cuspe of the fourth house; in the scheame of Heaven 1642/3. <hi>Feb.</hi> 15. when <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> made their last meeting in 25. 46. <hi>Pisces;</hi> the Sign <hi>Gemini</hi> did then descend on the cuspe of the seventh house, <hi>Mars</hi> being in one degree of <hi>Gemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> and the <hi>Moon</hi> 15. Let us now examine for instructions sake, even for our very friends, and worst of enemies, by way of exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the casualties have happened upon any eminent <hi>Conjunction</hi> of the <hi>Planets</hi> or <hi>Eclipses</hi> of the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon</hi> in or neer the degree of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> or in <hi>Opposition</hi> unto it; or in the degree of the <hi>Sun</hi> or <hi>Moon,</hi> at the time of that first <hi>Conjunction</hi> in 1603. and so successively in the second succeding and latter <hi>Conjunctions</hi> of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter.</hi> The 16. <hi>September</hi> 1604. <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> were in <hi>Conjunction</hi> in the tenth degree, and 17. <hi>Sagitarius,</hi> the 22. of <hi>October</hi> 1605. <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> were in <hi>Quartile</hi> in 23. <hi>Sagitarius,</hi> neer the place of the <hi>Moon</hi> in the first <hi>Conjunction,</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> in <hi>Virgo</hi> 14. degrees after, <hi>viz. November</hi> 5. <hi>Saturn</hi> that day transit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the very degree of the <hi>Moon;</hi> the Powder Treason should have been put into act. <hi>May</hi> 20. there was a <hi>Solan Eclipse</hi> in nine degrees of <hi>Gemini,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1612. <hi>Palsgrave</hi> came into <hi>England</hi> upon an unlucky aspect.</note> the sixteenth of <hi>October</hi> following arrived the PALS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GRAVE here in <hi>London; Saturn</hi> that day in eleven degrees of <hi>Pisces, viz.</hi> in <hi>quartile dexter</hi> to the <hi>conjunction</hi> of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> in 1603. and <hi>sinister quartile</hi> to the <hi>Moon</hi> in that <hi>conjunction:</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this his comming was any thing advantagious to our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we all know: however, the fourteenth of <hi>February</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:116730:22"/> he married the Lady <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the most gallant, and most heroick Lady of <hi>Europe,</hi> well meriting for her Husband a farre greater person: that day <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> being in a <hi>quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile</hi> aspect, <hi>Saturn</hi> in eighteen degrees of <hi>Pisces,</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> in <hi>Gemini.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the yeer 1618. a <hi>Comet</hi> appeared in <hi>England,</hi> in the moneth of <hi>November,</hi> the very Sign ascending at first sight of the <hi>Comet,</hi> and almost degree, <hi>viz.</hi> the nineteenth of <hi>Sagittary,</hi> being the self-same of the preceding first conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> in 1603. <hi>Saturn</hi> then running through <hi>Gemini,</hi> and very neer the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of this conjunction: In <hi>March</hi> following dyed Queen ANNE, a most gracious Queen, and King JAMES himself fell very sick, but recovered.</p>
               <p>In 1623. upon the second conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> the tenth degree of <hi>Sagittary</hi> did culminate, the opposite Sign and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of our present <hi>Conjunction:</hi> After which, <hi>viz.</hi> in 1625. dyed King <hi>James,</hi> and an heavy Plague in <hi>London</hi> succeeded; there fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in that yeer a <hi>Solar Eclipse</hi> in the seventeenth of <hi>Pisces,</hi> which Signe was intercepted in the ascendant, in the later conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> 1623. <hi>Saturn</hi> also that yeer transiting into the Sign <hi>Virgo,</hi> which is in <hi>quadrate</hi> to <hi>Sagittary,</hi> the Sign of the first conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and in <hi>quadrate</hi> to the <hi>Moon</hi> in that Figure: In 1635. <hi>Saturn</hi> transiting <hi>Sagittary,</hi> as also 1636. <hi>London</hi> smarted with the Plague in those yeers. Let us ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten to things fresh in memory, <hi>viz.</hi> that in 1639. there was a great Eclipse of the <hi>Sun</hi> in the tenth degree of <hi>Gemini,</hi> the <hi>Scots</hi> and we first then about that time began to quarrell, the Citizens of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> refuse to lend the King money to be imployed against the <hi>Scots:</hi> one Parliament is summoned during the effects of that <hi>Eclipse,</hi> as quickly dissolved; the Parliament scandalized by <hi>Finch,</hi> his Majesty discontented and angry; new stirs appear, and after that, the <hi>Scots</hi> invade us again; for where he fares well, he will stay longest, and we paid them then in mony, our Souldiers being then unwilling to beat them, but now they shal have blows, &amp;c. In 1640. when this Parliament began, the twentieth of <hi>Sagittary</hi> then culminated, and <hi>Pisces</hi> ascended, <hi>Mars</hi> in the tenth degree thereof, in <hi>quadrate dexter</hi> to the place of this Conjunction.</p>
               <p>I have wrote thus much onely to instruct the studious herein with the constant naturall progresse and key of heavenly <hi>Astrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie;</hi> which rightly understood and applied, will abundantly sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:116730:22"/> the carefull <hi>Astrologer:</hi> he that is master of more time then I am, may make further experiments in this kinde, even for many yeers or ages before our time; I assure him he will have no cause to repent his labour, so beneficially improved, as thereby it may, by what I have wrote, he may easily see that there hath been no manner of calamity befallen to this City or Kingdom since 1603. but there may be a significant reason in <hi>Astrologie</hi> given for it, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to naturall causes, either from the Conjunctions of the Planets, or Eclipses of the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon</hi> concurring with the <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix</hi> of the first, second or third Conjunction of the two superiors; and although so much knowledge was not left me by any <hi>Author,</hi> or derived from any ancient <hi>Writer,</hi> yet I out of the singlenesse of my heart, freely divulge this grand Key of <hi>Astrologie</hi> to Posterity, hoping it will produce greater things hereafter, when knowledge shall more abound.</p>
               <p>Nor could we have omitted what is immediately premised, unlesse we had given our selves liberty to be singular, and to abound in our own proper sense; a thing we delight not in, longer then our reason is seconded with <hi>Art:</hi> for many things are considerable in this <hi>Art,</hi> and severall wayes for discovery of truth, according to <hi>Rigel,</hi> Apho. 53. who saith, <hi>Fundamentum princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pale in revolutionibus annorum mundi, est introitus Solis, in primum punctum arietis, porro multa necessaria ad hanc inquisitionem sunt, &amp; seientia multo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, experimentorum &amp; cognitionum superiorum praeteritorum temporum &amp; magnarum Eclipsationum Profectionumque:</hi> The entrance of the <hi>Sun</hi> into the first point of <hi>Aries,</hi> is the principall and main founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in judging <hi>Revolutions</hi> of the yeers of the World; yet more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, there do many things also conduce unto this disquisition, as the knowledge of many Experiments, and the right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing of former and greater times elapsed; as also, the <hi>Eclipses,</hi> great <hi>Conjunctions</hi> and <hi>Profections:</hi> [by <hi>Profections,</hi> he intends the annuall Profection of the last preceding conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> the Sign ascending varying annually] as in 1642/3. the as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendant of the conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> was 27. 34. of <hi>Sagittarius,</hi> this yeer 1647/8. the 27. 34. of <hi>Taurus</hi> is the Profectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ascendant of that Conjunction; through which ascendant, or Sign of <hi>Taurus, Saturn</hi> by transit hath been passing with a slow motion above two full yeers, and the day of the <hi>Sun's</hi> ingresse in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Aries</hi> this yeer 1648. he did transit the degree and very minute almost of this Profectionall ascendant, afflicting thereby and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarding
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:116730:23"/> our Parliaments <hi>Designs:</hi> and furthermore, this present Conjunction of which I now treat, doth happen in <hi>Gemini,</hi> which is intercepted in the ascendant of this Profectionall <hi>Revolution</hi> of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter, ab hinc verè, ab hinc, lachrymae nostrae Anglicanae hoc tempore, non certè a Revolutione hujus ce Anni, vel ab hac tam dira &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midabili conjunctione infortunarum procedunt, sed Deus d-abit his quoque finem.</hi> I give also in the subsequent Discourse some further <hi>Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicall</hi> reason, why at present our State and this Kingdom is so disturbed, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And with great reason we do adhere unto this method, consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the regular and orderly disposition of the superiour Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figurations of all times, and in every yeer: <hi>Conjunctiones totius anni oppositionesque &amp; quadraturas si de qualitate temporis judicaturus sis, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse est ut consideres, per has autem causantur diversae transmutationes tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porum, viz.</hi> who will judge of the quality and condition of the time, it's necessary that he consider the <hi>Conjunctions, Oppositions</hi> and <hi>Quadratures</hi> of the whole yeer; that is, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th of the <hi>Luminaries</hi> and all the other Planets; for from hence are caused divers transmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the times.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are concerned in this Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note>These things generally premised, we now come to handle this <hi>Conjunction</hi> in a more particular way. In the first place we have but a sad position of heaven (which hath representation of the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament and their Members) to begin with; able utterly upon the first sight to startle and puzzle a weak affection, or any Astrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that is weak sighted, or that is but moderately minded to the actions and honor of this present Parliament, or that hath not better then humain principles; for we have <hi>Mars</hi> their <hi>Significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> because Lord of the As<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>endant in the eight house in <hi>Conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> with <hi>Saturn,</hi> a very sad Planet, nay, neer <hi>oculus Tauri,</hi> a further and more ill Omen, if not seriously considered, and artificially compared with other causes preceding and succeeding; verily the house it selfe wherein the <hi>Conjunction</hi> fals, is the worst place and house of the heavens, and most naturally and exactly signifies the sad and distracted condition of the present Parliament at this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry present time of the <hi>Conjunction;</hi> it well and singularly and cleerly imports the horrible and grand treacheries, multitude of distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances, and slippery clandestine designes both of many in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and in the severall Counties of <hi>England,</hi> yea, and in the very wals of their own houses at <hi>Westminster</hi> to ruine themselves and thereby their own Posterity, the Kingdome it selfe, this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:116730:23"/> and all our just Rights, which for the present we have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trusted them with. It implyes and points out a Parliament strug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and gasping for breath and life, wearied with labour and sadnesse, expecting more tumults, and daily more Novell diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bediences, affronts, and thwarting of their Authority, and crossing their designes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nulla divisio circuli tunc pessima tamque crudelis in omnibus quam octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va est, Rigel. Apho.</hi> 35. There is no part of the heavens so ill, so cruell and malicious in all things as the eighth house; and yet this is the very house wherein this <hi>Conjunction</hi> is at this time, and in which we finde <hi>Mars</hi> our Parliaments <hi>Significator</hi> in <hi>Conjunction</hi> with <hi>Saturne,</hi> the Author of all treachery and villany, and even such acts are now in agitation by such and such as <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> doe signifie, <hi>viz.</hi> their own Members, to bring this Parliament (the Kingdomes best Bulwarke against oppression and tyranny) to ruine and destruction. But let it be so, <hi>viz.</hi> that such things real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are intended at this present, and acting by some <hi>English</hi> Change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and Rennagadoes from <hi>English</hi> blood and glory, and from such as are degenerated from Christianity it selfe. And let our worst of enemies boast and humour their longing fancies, and sing Lullabye to their greedy expectations, depending upon the effects of this malevolent configuration; and let them prattle li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally and write innocently, and prophesie thunderingly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst us without understanding what dire and sad effects it may produce to our Parliament, the destruction whereof these villains onely ayme at, we give them leave to be mad, yea and drunke with their own fury. Let our soule proceed with sober judgement and impartiall arguments, and deale faithfully with all sorts of people of what quality so ever; what may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the dictates of this present <hi>Conjunction.</hi> As to the parts of this Kingdome, we say, it principally Designes the City of <hi>London,</hi> wherein many of the effects of this <hi>Conjunction</hi> shall manifest themselves; for unto the Signe of <hi>Gemini</hi> it is subject, as I could instance by infallible ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments of these and former ages. It also threatens the West of <hi>England,</hi> that part especially which is Mountainous, hilly, and rockie, verging somewhat to the South; as also the Eastern and Northeast part hereof; for I doe ever finde by experience that all ominous <hi>Eclipses</hi> and famous <hi>Conjunctions</hi> or <hi>Oppositions,</hi> greater or lesser <hi>(quoad)</hi> do as much prejudice those parts of the World, those Kingdomes, and Countries subject to the opposite Signes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:116730:24"/> the <hi>Conjunctions</hi> or <hi>Oppositions</hi> are, as much as those very Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries under the Signe it selfe, wherein the <hi>Conjunction, Opposition</hi> or <hi>Eclips,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Spain</hi> will suffer by this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction.</note> or <hi>Prodigie</hi> it selfe fals. And hereof <hi>Spaine</hi> was a sad wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in 1639. when there was an <hi>Eclips</hi> visible of the <hi>Sun</hi> in that very degree, <hi>viz.</hi> the eleventh of <hi>Gemini,</hi> after which, about five moneths they suffered the losse of their <hi>Armado</hi> on our coast. And much about that time our disquietnesse in the <hi>North</hi> began, and verily then also severall disorders and grievances in <hi>London</hi> were occasioned by the sharp <hi>Episcopals;</hi> for there's no mischief wherein either the hand or councell of a <hi>Priest</hi> is wanting; they are ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more readier for knavery then goodnesse, following their Bellies more then <hi>Divinity:</hi> From whence therefore we must expect in good earnest, infinite divisions and heart-burnings, as well amongst our great Ones at <hi>Westminster,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament shall not be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown.</note> they now residing within the orbs, as it were of this City, as amongst the principall Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, Magistrates and Commonalty of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and amongst the inferiour people, both City and Parliament will be miserably sensible thereof; yet however, the main body of this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and their authority (maugre all angry Devils and <hi>Scottish</hi> faction) shall be preserved and stand: but how the Citizens, being so vast a body, will guide their actions, and their Commonwealth, their Consultations and Body-politique, themselves being now the most active people in the Kingdom,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>London</hi> in danger.</note> incited mightily by the fury and heat of this sharp influence; or what shall casually happen to this City it self, occasioned by some popular tumultuous men, whom <hi>Posterity</hi> will curse, I will in part, and but in part discover, being more willing to offend by a tacite and still silence, then too much either to enrage an angry people, or discourage a religious society of men living amongst them; but in time a judgement sufficiently sharp, will descend from heaven upon some fiery spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, who for a time act wrong Councels, and destructive to the good of this famous City:<note place="margin">Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the City.</note> Let the wiser sort of Citizens consider well this succeeding Aphorism, and apply it home unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, every one as he is concerned in the place he undergoes, and that in time, and without partiality to themselves, or casting dirt in the <hi>Author's</hi> face, who entirely loves the Cities welfare; for it doth significantly expresse what shall in part chance to the City of <hi>London,</hi> ere the events signified hereby be quite over: <hi>In qualibet revolutione Civitatis vel Regni, in qua Signum ascendentis ceciderit in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titione octavae, &amp; directio illius temporis, ibi in ocava existens Mars, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delissimas
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:116730:24"/> esse dissensiones, &amp; effusionem sanginis in illa judicandum est,</hi> Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, Apho. 46. In every revolution of a City or Kingdom, in which the Sign of the ascendant of that City or Kingdom shall fall to be in the partition of the eighth house, and the Direction of that time shall be there, and also <hi>Mars,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Beware Citizens of violent Counsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours.</note> we may judge that there will be in that City or Kingdom most cruell divisions, and great shed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of blood. This is the <hi>English</hi> of the <hi>Aphorism</hi> without min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing or jugling, and without the infinite mercy of God, War and blood will succeed in this City, occasioned by a violent and obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Party, signified by <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars, viz.</hi> by the Souldier and the Commonalty, or inferiour people, or procured by Councels, or men violent rash and giddy, &amp;c. I pray God blesse us from the later prediction, the first we are sufficiently sensible of, (<hi>viz.</hi> dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentions) since <hi>Saturn</hi> entered <hi>Gemini,</hi> and have tasted of it; and our present actions invite, and give occasion to mistrust the later mischief, <hi>viz.</hi> the effusion of blood: <hi>Saturn</hi> is here best dignified, Almans. prop. 45. <hi>Cujuscunque natura Planetarum superior fuerit, non cessabit ejus actus usque quo sit ibidem ejus contrarium.</hi> Seg. 2. Apho. 103. <hi>Saturnus cum Oculo Tauri, magna detrimenta facit generaliier;</hi> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally <hi>Saturn</hi> with the <hi>Buls eye,</hi> is the presage of great mischief: These unfortunate Planets are both in <hi>quadrate platick</hi> to <hi>Jupiter;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Great ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities to ensue.</note> from which position and aspect, let us expect infinite and endlesse Disputes and Controversies about our Laws, Customs and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, about Religion, and with the Religious, about Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, Leagues, Jurisdictions, &amp;c. It shews fears, jealousies, mistrusts, great waste and consumption os mens Estates, especially in this City, decay of Houses, Trades, sequestration of Revenues, the destruction and extirpation of whole Families, and they very ancient, the firing and destruction of many Houses, and of some Cities and Towns, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Almans.</hi> 60. <hi>Ea que accidunt in hoc seculo, sciuntur &amp; investigantur ex magna fortitudine superioris significatoris &amp; ex sua elevatione.</hi> Mundane affaires, or such things as happen in this world, are known and discovered by the great strength of the superior <hi>Significator,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dearth and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine.</note> and by his Elevation. From the sence and construction of this A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorisme, there arises thus much; as <hi>Saturn</hi> is better dignified then <hi>Mars,</hi> we must expect a Famine and a Dearth, or scarcity of Provisions, intemperate cold blasts, great infidelity generally, as well in the Parliament and their Members, as in the City and Countrey, and prime men of every place. As <hi>Mars</hi> is most eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:116730:25"/> he shewes the Sword will prevaile, though much interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Countermands, contrary directions and Commissions; in plaine termes, it animates the Souldier, though with a fearfull or mistrustfull conception of the event of his Actions; yea, it ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues in the end,<note place="margin">The Army ordained to stand, and do the Kingdom good.</note> the Army will be enforced to doe strange things, else we must perish, and themselves likewise. Who ever therefore hath naturall <hi>English</hi> blood in him, let him take part with the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my under the Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> and with the Parliament; so shall he live and have a being, and doe his owne Prince and Kingdome service, and restore <hi>England</hi> to its pristine glory; at present much Eclipsed by some snarling <hi>Scottified</hi> people of late encroaching upon us.<note place="margin">The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to join with the Army.</note> And certainly here is some greater works neer at hand, then onely the dispute of Customes or divesting some great ones of their Estates, by reason of the transmutation of the <hi>Auge</hi> of <hi>Mars,</hi> who is <hi>Significator</hi> of this Kingdome, and Lord of the As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendant in this <hi>Conjunction:</hi> For I doe finde in <hi>Rigel, Apho.</hi> 9. <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantur regna &amp; Dominia, &amp; fides, Sectaeque, &amp; opiniones hominum. Dum mutantur auges planetarum, de signo in signum dico, illarum gentium qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Significator erit planeta augis per mutatae, mutatioque erit ad bonum vel ad malum secundum naturam significatorum conjunctionum superiorum illorum temporum &amp; secundum naturam signi mutationis.</hi> In <hi>English</hi> thus, Kingdoms and Governments, Leagves, Sects, and the opinions of Men doe change or vary, when the <hi>Auges</hi> of the Planets move out of one Signe into another; I say of those Nations whose <hi>Signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tator</hi> is the Planet of the transmutated <hi>Auges,</hi> and this alteration shall be for good or ill,<note place="margin">A trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation of govern-to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected.</note> according to the nature of the <hi>Significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> of the superior Conjunctions of those times, and according to the nature of the Signe of mutation.</p>
               <p>But lest one example or <hi>Aphorisme</hi> might be thought an incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent judge herein; the matter we now handle being weighty and of mighty consideration, and the times capable of this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, we produce <hi>Cardane seg.</hi> 1. <hi>Apho.</hi> 37. <hi>Per mutationes Absidum, regna, &amp; regiones, &amp; religiones mutant, &amp; Planetae, vel Ascendens in his vel oppositis, vim à natura ejus contrahunt, cujus est Absis, puram in abside, depravatam in opposito, convenit igitur hos scire.</hi> The permuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or variations of the Absides of the Planets, change King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and Regions, alter Religions; and either the Planets themselves or the <hi>Ascendant</hi> being in these Signes, or their Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sites, contract vertue from the nature of the Signe whose <hi>Absis</hi> it is; pure vertue and influence in the <hi>Absis</hi> it selfe, or Sign wherein
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:116730:25"/> it is, depraved and corrupt in its opposite Sign. It is necessary to know this manner of learning; should I explain this, it were a labour of a sheet of paper, but my time is limited; I shall make use of it in our Judgement, which will be sufficient: I onely say, that <hi>Mars</hi> is the generall Significator of <hi>England,</hi> and that at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent his <hi>Absis</hi> or <hi>Aphelium</hi> is in four Signs, twenty nine degrees, fifty two minutes and twenty one seconds; that is, in twenty nine degrees, fifty two minutes, and twenty one seconds of <hi>Leo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Virgo</hi> the ascendant of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gl sh</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy.</note> and that in the yeer 1656. his <hi>Aphelium</hi> will be in <hi>Virgo,</hi> and he then leaves the Sign <hi>Leo; Virgo</hi> is assuredly the ascendant of the <hi>English Monarchy,</hi> but <hi>Aries</hi> of the Kingdom: when this <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sis</hi> therefore of <hi>Mars</hi> shall appear in <hi>Virgo;</hi> who shall expect lesse then a strange <hi>Catastrophe</hi> of humane affairs in this Common-wealth, <hi>Monarchy</hi> and Kingdom of <hi>England?</hi> for how can <hi>Mars</hi> shew or give protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to <hi>Aries</hi> or <hi>Virgo,</hi> which Signs he beholds not with any aspect? here will then either in or about those times, or neer that yeer, or within ten yeers more or lesse of that time,<note place="margin">Great change neer 1656</note> or within a little time after, appear in this Kingdom so strange a <hi>Revolution</hi> of fate, so grand a <hi>Catastrophe,</hi> and great mutation unto this <hi>Monarchy</hi> and Government, as never yet appeared; of which (as the times now stand) I have no liberty or encouragement to deliver my opinion. Onely it will be ominous to <hi>London,</hi> unto her Merchants at Sea, to her traffique at land, to her Poor, to her Rich, to all sorts of people inhabiting in her, or her Liberties, by reason of sundry fires, and a consuming Plague, &amp;c. But I fear a sad disaster to this City much before that time; to reveal it, were cause of envy;<note place="margin">It may be extended to signifie the change of many now in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, for there are few Kings to be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and men in authority are as it were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative Kings.</note> to conceal it, is a point of humane Policy. In the intervall of which time, if it be lawfull to quote <hi>Almansor,</hi> Apho. 132. <hi>Cum duae infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunae conjunguntur &amp; Luna Saturno in latitudine, erit fames &amp; mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, si vero Marti mutabuntur Reges, &amp; erit multa sanguinis effusio, &amp; praelia in loco qui signabitur ab ipso Signo &amp; hoc non fallit:</hi> when the two <hi>Infortunes</hi> are in conjunction, and the <hi>Moon</hi> concur with <hi>Saturn</hi> in latitude, there will ensue a famine and mortality, (both which I much fear unto the City of <hi>London:</hi>) but if she concur with <hi>Mars,</hi> (which in this <hi>Conjunction</hi> she doth not) Kings or Governours shall be changed, and there will be much spilling of blood, many Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tails, or much fighting, in that very place which is signified by that very Sign it self, wherein this <hi>Conjunction</hi> is; and this fails not.</p>
               <p>This is a friendly admonition to the industrious Citizens of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:116730:26"/>
                  <hi>London,</hi> who are the most of any in <hi>Europe</hi> concerned in the effects of this <hi>Conjun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tion;</hi> the Sign <hi>Gemini,</hi> as I have said, being the ascen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant of their City. I shall not willingly expatiate or dilate upon the plain meaning of these words; the Aphorism being so signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, and the Citizens of so great capacities, so prudent and judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, as there is no doubt, if God have not obfuscated their judgements, and clouded their <hi>Senators</hi> wisdom, they will be mindefull of my words;<note place="margin">The City poysoned with Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants.</note> though now at this present I am held of a contrary opinion to most of them, who busily endeavour the disturbance of the City (the contrary whereof I love) but it is the poysonous breath of <hi>Malignants,</hi> or a few fellow-Citizens of fiery dispositions, co-inhabiting together with vertuous men, and more graver judgements, that have so obstructed the glory of the City at this present, and clouded their former actions (which indeed were most honourable) and brought them now (in the opinion of very many) under the notion of <hi>Self-seekers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Citizens not belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of the Countrey.</note> and the Kingdoms Disturbers; and so great an <hi>odium</hi> lyes upon this City at present, generally throughout this whole Kingdom, that it is a great wonder unto me (I mean the Countries ill affection to the City) of which, by continuall Letters from severall parts I understand, and did personally hear, and was an eye witnesse at my being at the Leaguer before <hi>Colchester, July</hi> 1648. the <hi>Essex</hi> men generally as much enraged against this City,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Essex</hi> men disconten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens sent no ayde to the Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed it, they say they ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not the City so when the King was at <hi>Brainford.</hi>
                  </note> as they against the Parliament: yet I desire not to live any longer then I should endeavour and wish all prosperity to the Body and Common-wealth of this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that it may abundantly flourish in <hi>Trade, Commerce</hi> and <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility,</hi> &amp;c. The least accident that can happen unto this City now at present from this <hi>Conjunction,</hi> is Sedition, Tumults and Uproars, Famine, if no blood-shed: for it is generally beleeved, that any Conjunction of the three Superiours in an ayery Sign, <hi>Ventos &amp; seditiones pestilentiamque, sed non tamen semper movet,</hi> Card. Seg. 7. Apho. 34. high Windes are signified (as to the Weather) Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, Tumults, Hurlyburlies, and the Pestilence (as to the City) by any <hi>Conjunction</hi> in an ayery Sign, <hi>Portenditur etiam multorum homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num interritus ex peste;</hi> which I verily beleeve shall prove true within the compasse of two yeers, and ere this <hi>Conjunction</hi> have done ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating, for so long time the influence hereof continues.</p>
               <p>Having now delivered what the opinion of <hi>Authors</hi> is concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this malevolent <hi>Conjunction</hi> in generall, let us a little give leave to our <hi>Genius</hi> to be studious herein, and to expatiate our thoughts,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:116730:26"/> that we (the least of <hi>Students</hi>) may leave Posterity a small remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of our indefatigable labours in this study of <hi>Astrologie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesied of by <hi>Merlin</hi> 900. yeers since.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our time sinking, in a fair way, now by our industry of revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving. I will begin gently with his Majesty, whose sufferings were ordained many ages since, as I daily finde in many old <hi>Prophesies:</hi> his <hi>Significator</hi> in this Scheam is very properly the <hi>Sun,</hi> as he is Lord of the tenth, who now is locally placed in the ninth house of heaven, but in the twelfth from the tenth; that is, in that house which signifies restraint of liberty, or in plain terms, <hi>captivity,</hi> &amp;c. (and so is he captived at this time) there is <hi>Jupiter</hi> in the tenth house powerfull (<hi>quoad</hi> accidentally) not essentially; <hi>Ergo,</hi> it's not words, but money that buyes Land; it's not the delusive pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises of his false friends, whereof he hath ever had too many, es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially of the <hi>Scots</hi> Nation, or probably,<note place="margin">The King impedited by the <hi>Scots,</hi> and by tumults <hi>Paris</hi> must expect present tumults:</note> the intended assistance of his own children, signified by <hi>Jupiter,</hi> as he is Lord partly of the fifth from the tenth, can effect his liberty, or his restauration, or will <hi>France</hi> do the work; I see no sufficient willingnesse in that people, or abilities, if willing: for we see <hi>Jupiter</hi> in <hi>quartile</hi> to <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> and they in the eighth; one misfortune in the neck of another, one miscarriage after another amongst his friends; for a time and a long season blasts all assistance and hopes of friends, and all his Majesties own Designs and affairs; I mean, by means of War or Souldiers.</p>
               <p>There is a full measure of time limited by God, which being not as yet accomplished, renders in the interim, all mans endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour fruitlesse, and his labour impertinent, God of his goodnesse shorten it for the good of us all; yet, its my opinion, were there not more then a naturall hand, and not a Divine power superla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively transcending celestiall <hi>Configurations,</hi> the approaching of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> to a <hi>Sextill</hi> of <hi>Iupiter</hi> in this figure at the time of the aspect, she then in <hi>Sagittary,</hi> there should arise very many faire and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table promises, and very many Missives from friends,<note place="margin">A <hi>Sextile</hi> of <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> Octob. 29 1648. then good hopes for his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty.</note> or assistance from severall parts; some from <hi>France,</hi> because <hi>Iupiter</hi> is in <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go</hi> the ascendant of <hi>Paris:</hi> others from <hi>Scotland,</hi> because <hi>Venus</hi> is in <hi>Cancer.</hi> But as the <hi>Moon,</hi> who is Lady of that house, doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold <hi>Cancer,</hi> and not the <hi>Sun,</hi> so shall the <hi>Scots</hi> now in Armes, more regard their own private interests, lucre, stealing and filch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing, then his Majesties restauration; and the <hi>French</hi> will rather seem to act, then doe any thing really, having worke enough at home. But that his friends may, can, or shall reinthronize his
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:116730:27"/> Majesty by War,<note place="margin">His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty best to depend on the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament and Army, not on the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
                  </note> or Tumults, against the intentions of this very Parliament <hi>(statu quo)</hi> its negative in <hi>Astrologie,</hi> and a lye, if the drowsie Malignant Prophets pipe otherwise; therefore his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty must depend upon the uprightnesse and moderation of his Parliament and their Army; all whose hearts God of his mercy incline to doe justice equally without partiality; very little on the City of <hi>London,</hi> the Magistrates whereof being not ordained generally to concur, and besides, their Divisions seeming to be very many, one party still impeding and crossing another; nor are their Consultations ordained to be the restorers of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty or Monarchy, what ever their owne haughty desires may suggest unto themselves, either of their personall valours, or Purse abilities <hi>(sic est Statutum;)</hi> so that in few words, I say, this <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction</hi> is not the antecedent, or precursor of inlargement to his Majesties person, or restauration to former dignities by any manner of meanes,<note place="margin">The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire for Peace, and setling his Majesty.</note> but a Treaty, for <hi>Iupiter</hi> is his onely friend, and is the Author of Councell and Justice, Peace and tranquili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. I pray God give us both a Treaty, and Peace to succeed it, the thing I onely wish for in this World. Those must either be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from other causes and configurations, or not be thought on from hence.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Successe of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>And now I am to handle this Scheme of heaven, and this <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction</hi> as it hath any relation or any thing to doe with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Parliament and Commonalty of <hi>England,</hi> who now regulate our unsetled,<note place="margin">Fixed Signs ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</note> disordered and dis-joyted affai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es. The <hi>Ascendant</hi> of this <hi>Conjunction</hi> is the third of <hi>Scorpio,</hi> a fixed Sign, so are all the angles of the Figure; its in <hi>Pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>icke trine</hi> unto the fourth of <hi>Pisces,</hi> Ascending at time of their first sitting 1640. <hi>Ergo,</hi> the body of this Parliament shall stand firme, shall not be <hi>potentially</hi> or <hi>actually dissipated.</hi> But <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Saturn,</hi> which signifies the Members of both Houses,<note place="margin">Members questiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> shews great fear and mistrusts in them, and that many of them shall totter, shake and be questioned, and found faulty, not of innocency, but of connivancy with the <hi>Scots,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Untill some guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery in both hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses be found out, we shall suffer.</note> of horrible Plots, and high misdemenors, of treachery a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the very being of the whole Parliament. Its not a time now in this present exigent of time, or my custome to flatter any. In the name of God, let the guilty betrayers of Publick trust and selfe-seekers finde equall justice with the worst of Malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors; whoever he be, Lord or no Lord, Knight or no Knight, that wrongs or abuses the trust reposed in him by the Common-wealth;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:116730:27"/> let him dye the death; the most shamefullest of deaths. The sword of the Almighty, the just fury of the angry and ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed People; the uncouth clamour of thousands cry out against many of them; Justice must be done, it must not be delayed or prolonged; some must dye, some must disgracefully be turned out of their Places (for we have been and are still betrayed by some in Authority;) some must be fleeced or let blood of such stocks of Money, as have been knavishly and theevishly purloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from the miserable Common-wealth. Committee men, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>questrators, <hi>unjust Treasurers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Many peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stioned.</note> Receivers and Disposers of the Kings Revenues, the <hi>venerable Excisers,</hi> my <hi>quondam Enemies;</hi> all must to the Bar of Justice.</p>
               <p>The influence of this <hi>Conjunction</hi> will squeez many hundreds of pounds from such men, to the great content of the whol King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and I hope satisfaction of Gods wrath, who will be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly pleased with our Parliament when they administer equal Justice, and first begin with themselves; these things being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed will prove an exc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eding benefit unto the valiant Souldier; who by such Mens meanes and the shi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>king devises formerly of Treasu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers and Subtreasurers, have been fed with a bitt and a kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cke. Yet let no Man imagine by these words, I dislike the afor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>said callings, <hi>viz.</hi> ei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Excize or S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>questration of them who deserve it, the present State having occasion of moneys, no, I do not: I on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quarrell a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the abus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and unjustnesse of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of these Officers; and I desire the State to give a full and free liberty for such men to be questioned, and all thos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> especially,<note place="margin">This I know to be t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ue by m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> very friend, Mr. <hi>B.</hi>
                  </note> that under the notion of <hi>Sequ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>strators</hi> revenge their own p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ivate quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell or malice upon the miserable S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bject, making their own ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>linque<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts, upon no sufficient gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>und, but inveterate hatred of their own, whereby some mens estates are kept sequestrated two or three yeers, and by policy and indirect means, impeded, that they cannot be heard before the Lords and Commons of that Committee, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The ponderous effects of this malevolent <hi>Conjunction,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Much trouble to the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> though they shall much, and for a long time amuse and stumble this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and especially the honourable house of Commons, by reason of the many and infinite backslidings in the people them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and Members of their own house, and losses which they shall for a while sustain, and the daily and weekly contumelies, scandals, irreverent affronts in point of honour, they and seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:116730:28"/> of their Members shall undergo: yet notwithstanding, fear not <hi>English Parliament,</hi> be not dismayed noble house of <hi>Commons, VIVE, VIVE, VIVE,</hi> thou shalt stand firm and immovable, like unto the stately Oak,<note place="margin">The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to continue long.</note> which scorns to buckle: it's true, some of thy rotten boughs, and unfaithful branches shall be lopt off from thee (I would they had never been of thee;) but as the main body of the tall and sturdy Oak stands untottered, or unshaken, against all blustering opposition of impetuous storms, and furious tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pests; so shall thy main <hi>Fabrick:</hi> although many shall thy suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings be, and thy patience as much; yea, even infinite! yet thou shalt overcome, and in the end acquire thy desires; and in thee, and by thy endeavours,<note place="margin">The whole Kingdom happy in the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament and Army.</note> with this poor Army now so scorned, the whole Common-wealth of the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> even to a full perfection, and to the content of the greatest part of the Kingdom shall be blessed; which they will acknowledge, when God shall open their eyes to discern what is good for them.</p>
               <p>Nor let any Object unto me, that this is the worst <hi>Conjunction</hi> of Heaven, and these two Planets the worst of <hi>Significators</hi> for our Parliament, and thereby no such good can come unto them: Let these men speake on, but I wish them to consider what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes; <hi>Quando duae infortunae conjunguntur, fit ex eis fortuna perfecta, sicut ex duarum fortunarum conjunctione, &amp; hoc secundum dicta Ptolomei,</hi> Almansor Apho. 7. When two Infortunes are conjoyned (as now they are) there proceeds from thence or from their influences a perfect Fortune;<note place="margin">Good to our Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from this ill Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> even as there doth from the <hi>Conjunction</hi> of the two Fortunes: this is according to <hi>Ptolomie.</hi> Besides, we know God almighty many times suffers to be produced good from evil. So then, let the weekly <hi>Mercurian</hi> Prophets, descant according to their manner of lying, upon this <hi>Conjunction,</hi> which they pretend to be so fatall to our <hi>Parliament,</hi> and let them with open mouthes and nasty pens deride my Predictions. I say it denotes, after a small expence of time, much happinesse (the Nationall misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune considered) augmentation of friends,<note place="margin">The <hi>Scots</hi> threatned.</note> and a glorious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest of such as shall rise against them; yea, of <hi>Iockey Scot</hi> and <hi>Hamilton</hi> the unfortunate, and of as many forward men of any City, County or Countrey as shall presume to rise in Armes to offend or disturbe their Consultations, or blast their Army and its honour with reproaches, whether verball or otherwise. And were there ever a <hi>Mercury</hi> against us of any judgement, or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of my anger or labour, I would openly against him and all
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:116730:28"/> of them dispute the point in question, before never so great an <hi>Auditory</hi> (be they Schollers or Gentlemen) even of their own best friends, &amp;c. But as nasty <hi>vermine,</hi> borne to destruction, I scorne nomination of the best of that beggerly crew of drunken <hi>Sots,</hi> who live by writing lyes against the honour of our Parliament; an account whereof they must give to God one day, &amp;c. But I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire all along to be charitably understood, concerning the event and successe of my Predictions; for my meaning still is (not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termedling with Gods divine providence) but as farre as may be seen by naturall causes in <hi>Astrologie,</hi> that such things shall come to passe. For its most true which <hi>Dasipodius Aphorisme</hi> 14. hath; <hi>Major est vis astrorum quam ut quisquam eam estimare possit, nam legum &amp; imperiorum mutationes &amp; naturae miracula (non inquam illa que divina fiunt providentia) quae varii ad varia referunt, ab his prodeunt.</hi> The vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour and influence of the Stars and Planets, and their vertue, is greater then any can well imagine; for the mutations of Laws and Kingdomes, and the Miracles of Nature proceed from hence; (I meane not those which are Miraculously disposed by Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, or a Divine hand;) the former changes I say come from influence of the Planets, though many refer them to other causes.</p>
               <p>But if it be Objected, How comes the Parliament into so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny afflictions, even at present time before this <hi>Conjunction?</hi> First, without doubt its Gods judgment upon this Kingdome. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, according to nature its thus, <hi>viz.</hi> that at this time of our <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, Mars,</hi> the generall <hi>Significator</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> is Cadent from <hi>Aries</hi> his owne house; a thing very unfortunate, I confesse, as it is well observed by <hi>Bethem</hi> Apho. 14. <hi>Quando Planeta est cadens a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo sua, aut a domo exaltationis est ut vir, &amp;c.</hi> When a Planet is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from his own House, or the House of his exaltation; he is like a Man absent from his dwelling house, or from his owne Towne or City. This may excellently be applyed to our present affaires; for while our Armies are the one at <hi>Colchester,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hamilton</hi> and some <hi>Scots</hi> the cause of our trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> the other in <hi>Wales,</hi> there appeares an Enemy in the <hi>North, viz.</hi> Sir <hi>Marma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke Langdale,</hi> and in <hi>Iuly</hi> the unluckie-<hi>Hamilton</hi> and his ragged <hi>Scottish</hi> Army came over <hi>Tweed,</hi> all whom I trust God will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found, as enemies and destroyers of those good men in <hi>Scotland,</hi> our true Brethren, that have so much courage and conscience, as to say, his engagement against us, is wholly unlawfull, and who by this intrusion indeavours the breach of that League which
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:116730:29"/> hath continued betwixt us five and forty yeers, to the great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the whole people of <hi>Scotland;</hi> so that herein this A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorisme hath its full influence, and effect.</p>
               <p>But yet notwithstanding the <hi>Scots invasion</hi> and <hi>Londons failings,</hi> and those extream misfortunes which have of late, and shal further presse our <hi>Parliament</hi> in their aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>irs; yet seriously considering eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular which might <hi>conduce</hi> to our support, I finde that the good <hi>hand</hi> of <hi>God</hi> will not suffer them to be destroyed,<note place="margin">Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to flourish, maugre all their their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</note> for he hath ordained the North <hi>Node</hi> of <hi>Venus</hi> to be in the thirteenth degree of <hi>Gemini,</hi> and in the same <hi>Sign, viz.</hi> in five degrees, the <hi>Caput Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conis</hi> of <hi>Jupiter</hi> is: so that miraculously, and by the immediate and out-stretched <hi>hand</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and by <hi>means</hi> and <hi>men</hi> contemptible, our <hi>Parliament</hi> shall continue, and not be overthrown, massacred, or enforced to flye, or submit to base or slavish terms, or treaties (I mean such as be <hi>unbeseeming</hi> for them) or the <hi>unnec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ssary directions</hi> and <hi>Petitions</hi> of busie men, and <hi>hairbrained</hi> fellows, who <hi>print</hi> their own sordid <hi>conceptions</hi> as Directories to our <hi>Parliament:</hi> I pray <hi>God</hi> they will now at <hi>length</hi> make good use of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir time, and of all happy <hi>occasions</hi> whereby we may come to a happy <hi>Ʋnion</hi> with his <hi>Majesty,</hi> and of a right <hi>understanding</hi> of all such things <hi>conducing</hi> to the welfare of this tottered and disl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cated Kingdom, as may be <hi>convenient,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">How it concerns the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</note> &amp;c. Amongst the <hi>common people</hi> this shews great <hi>murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, repining, discontent</hi> and giddy <hi>resolutions,</hi> apt to revolt or take any <hi>part,</hi> or to receive any <hi>impr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ssion,</hi> gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at fears and jealousies, losse in their Cattle and Corn, &amp;c. But sith both <hi>Planets</hi> are swift in <hi>motion,</hi> I hope these great mischiefs shall not fix any great space of time, but shall grow lesse and lesse about thirty five weeks after the day of the very <hi>Conjunction</hi> it self:<note place="margin">Great hopes in 150. days. of subd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing our e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>emies.</note> and if this defection or mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief be not by <hi>Providence</hi> intended generall, I hope about one hundred fifty five dayes to be accompted from the <hi>Conjunction,</hi> we shall have in some measure subdued many of our enemies; yet shall not we then come to a finall end, or to a period of our troubles; for <hi>Operationes Planetarum nunquam cessant, donec contrario a Planeta vel Stella fixa, aut Signi parte contrariae qualitatis impediantur vel in Solis radios incidunt,</hi> Card. Seg. 2. Apho. 63. The influence of the <hi>Planets</hi> never cease operating, untill impedited by some Planet or fixed Star of a contrary nature to those which preceded, or untill the Planet who is principall <hi>Significator</hi> fall into <hi>combustion:</hi> We have no forcible aspect to mitigate these sad disasters, untill by tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sit <hi>Jupiter</hi> about the two and twentieth of <hi>August,</hi> seemeth by his
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:116730:29"/>
                  <hi>Sextile</hi> aspect unto <hi>Mars,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Good to be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament in the latter end of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust,</hi> and in <hi>Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> 1648.</note> to allay and diminish part of these evils now raging: but in regard that very day the <hi>Moon</hi> suffers three <hi>oppositions, viz.</hi> of the <hi>Sun, Venus</hi> and <hi>Mercury,</hi> that <hi>Sextile</hi> aspect produceth little good, unlesse some rout or knocking of the mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Scots</hi> in the North: About the middle of <hi>September</hi> both <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> and the <hi>Sun</hi> aspect <hi>Mars</hi> with their <hi>Sextile,</hi> but it's in such pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of heaven, that it onely supports and keeps us alive, but gives no absolute Victory, or not such a knocking one as my heart wishes; but in the latter end of <hi>September,</hi> and beginning of <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> or neer or before those times, we have very good hopes, either totally or in great measure of defeating all, or most of our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, both <hi>Cavaliers</hi> and <hi>blew-Bonnets,</hi> and to send them home as empty of plunder as they were of honesty when they came in.</p>
               <p>But now let us see in generall,<note place="margin">Tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Weather.</note> what this <hi>Conjunction</hi> may signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, as unto the temperature of Weather, and season of the yeer, &amp;c. according to <hi>Albumazar,</hi> Diff. 8. <hi>Mars si fuerit Dominus anni &amp; in aërea Triplicitate</hi> (as now of the remainder of the yeer he is, <hi>viz.</hi> from the ingresse of the <hi>Sun</hi> into <hi>Cancer) si fuerit Directus, &amp; non aspexerit ascendens, significat plurimas oombustiones &amp; nocumentum ab igni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, &amp; aegritudines qaae adveniunt hominibus causa sanguinis, &amp; destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem vegitabilium causa valetudinis ventorum: Mars,</hi> as now posited, signifies many Combustions, hurt by Fire, Sicknesses to man by reason of corrupted blood, no great good to the vegetable Plants of the earth. Somewhat to the same purpose he delivers of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition of <hi>Saturn</hi> in <hi>Gemini; Qui si non aspexerit ascendens significat fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ventorum ineessanter &amp; fortitudinem eorum, &amp;c.</hi> But when this conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> is in <hi>Gemini,</hi> and in the second or eighth, <hi>significat destructionem censuum, depressionem famae divitum &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parentiam egestatis &amp; paupertatis &amp; debilitatis in plebibus: viz.</hi> unusu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Windes shall arise, and they incessantly molest us, &amp;c. the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> in the eighth house or second,<note place="margin">Nobility imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished.</note> inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates an impoverishment in the Revenues of the rich men, and a depression of their fame and esteem, and an appearance of poverty in many of the common sort of people. And because <hi>Scorpio</hi> is the ascendant of this Conjunction, you shall hear the opinion of the same Author; <hi>Cum Scorpio ascenderit tempore conjunctionis alicujus dua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum infortunarum apparebunt in Civitatibus super quas est (Almuzfauli) Reges pulchrarum facierum, prodigi multas expendentes pecunias &amp; coitus; &amp; multiplicabun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur Philosophi, &amp; Paraletici, &amp; Medicinae, &amp; ingenia ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum pauca fient in rebus quas perscrutabuntur, &amp; multiplicabuntur guer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:116730:30"/> &amp; bella &amp; Depredationes insceleritate, &amp; acuitas, &amp; levitas, &amp; Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus, &amp; carcer, &amp; carcerati, &amp; angustiae, &amp; tristitiae; &amp; proditio, &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusatio, &amp; mixturatio, &amp; interfectio, &amp; aegritudines, &amp; accident tenebrae in hora post horam; corroborabitur frigus hyemis &amp; flabunt in mediatate ejus venti occidentales, &amp; multiplicabuntur in eo pluviae, &amp; significat mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum timorem in pluribus terris.</hi> When the Sign of <hi>Scorpio</hi> shall ascend at the time of a Conjunction of the two <hi>Infortunes,</hi> there will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in those Kingdoms, Cities or Countries whereof he is prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall <hi>Significator,</hi> Kings, or Princes, or Magistrates pretending fair, men prodigall, expending much treasure, many confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; there will abound many learned men, or Philosophers, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny will have the Palsie,<note place="margin">Wars to be e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.</note> or Falling-evil, much use there will be of Physick, few mens endeavours shall attain the ends they desire; Wars and slaughters shall be multiplied, many depredations or inroads, with much wickednesse; much sharpnesse, great levity and dolefull laments shall be amongst men, much woe and misery to those imprisoned, and many captived; there will be treachery and accusing one another, mixing one ill act with another, killing one another, great store of sicknesse, a dark ayre, and ill season day after day; the cold of Winter will be extream, and in the midst of Winter the West Winde will blow boysterously, many showrs will fall; the mindes of men in divers parts of the Kingdom will be extream fearfull, and quite out of order. How really this judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath in part been verified,<note place="margin">Major <hi>Hunting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> censu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> I need not mention in any other thing then in Major <hi>Huntington</hi> his malicious slander of Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant generall <hi>Cromwell;</hi> yet is that simple Accusation hug'd and entertained most willingly. I forbear that aspersion cast upon Major <hi>Rolfe,</hi> in regard many of the adverse Party beleeve it not, and of another valiant Souldier of Colonel <hi>Riches</hi> Regiment, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cused by no better a witnesse then a mad woman. But we shall not be alwayes unhappy, for God will deliver our Army from the hands of such as would willingly hang them, for their service done to the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Arabick</hi> Authors most of them concur in this manner of judgement, and indeed I do more relye upon those significations attending the influence of <hi>Mars,</hi> then of <hi>Saturn,</hi> because he is Lord of the ascendant in this Conjunction, and of the remainder of this yeer in the annuall Revolution: this is my opinion, grounded upon reason; and if the event prove contrary, I wish the <hi>Ancients</hi> had left us better presidents: for it is most true that <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:116730:30"/> observed of <hi>Ptolomey,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Generall accidents not hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by <hi>Pto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomey</hi> suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently.</note>
                  <hi>Tractatus de mundi rebus generalibus tenuius a</hi> Ptolomeo <hi>traditus est, quam pro tanto negotio expediret:</hi> viz. <hi>Ptolomey</hi> left that part of <hi>Astrologie</hi> lame, or wrote of it very slenderly, which handled the <hi>Revolution</hi> of the world, and generall accidents there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto belonging: yet there might be some reason given for it: for in <hi>Ptolomey's</hi> time, the whole earth knew no more but one Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and he of <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp;c. it might as well be objected, <hi>Homerus non vidit omnia,</hi> it's not an easie labour, or as yet have there been any have waded far into it.</p>
               <p>But time will enlarge more Authors; and indeed Antiquity is much to be discommended, either for revealing so little, or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scuring so great a benefit from us; for <hi>Escuidus</hi> (who onely of all the Ancients writes most copiously of Revolutions onely upon a <hi>Conjunction</hi> of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> wherein <hi>Mars</hi> is elevated above <hi>Saturn</hi> in <hi>Gemini,</hi> saith, <hi>Multae guerrae, multae aegritudines &amp; mors in eis; Pluviae, tonitrua, &amp; corruscationes,</hi> page 32. Many Wars, much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, many sicknesses and death ensuing from thence, rain, thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, sights, apparitions, or Meteors in the Ayre; the words in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed are significant, yet short. But <hi>Albumasar</hi> had he been right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Translated, I conceive, had spoke more truth; for he saith, <hi>Mars</hi> in <hi>Gemini Dolores aurium in hominibus, &amp; variolas, &amp; Morbillos, &amp; interfectionem in septentrionem, cum multo Latracinio, &amp; eruntnocumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta hominibus, preter tonitrua &amp; coruscationes, causa vehementis frigoris, &amp;c. Mars</hi> and <hi>Gemini</hi> imports much infirmity in Peoples eares, the small Pox and Measels, slaughter in the North,<note place="margin">Bloodshed in the North.</note> much theevish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; Men will also suffer many other detriments by reason of the excesse of cold weather. And besides, in his <hi>Flores,</hi> he saith, <hi>Si Saturnus in Gemini erit, &amp; Latitudo Meridionalis &amp; etiam Orientalis à sole significat calorem temporis, cum paucitate pluviarum &amp; multitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Pestilentiarum, &amp; multos morbos mortalium, &amp; infirmitatem regum &amp; magnatum; &amp; si Mars in eodem signo, fuerit &amp; Orientalis, multitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem pluviarum &amp; pustularum hominum.</hi> By reason of the mixture of <hi>Mars</hi> with <hi>Saturne,</hi> much Raine; <hi>Saturn</hi> in <hi>Gemini</hi> alone sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies no such thing; here is signified the Pestilence amongst men; an infirmity afflicting Kings and Nobles; aboundance of people languishing with the small Pox.</p>
               <p>I shall say something concerning the City of <hi>London</hi> in the words of an Author of no mean esteem, <hi>viz. Johannes Escuidus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Somewhat to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
                  </note> page 39. When you find a <hi>Conjuction</hi> of the superiors in <hi>Gemini,</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:116730:31"/> or an <hi>Eclips</hi> in that Sign. <hi>Apparebit in civitatibus &amp; regionibus su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per quas est signum Geminorum Dominator: nimia consideratio in scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiis; etiam quae sunt super naturam ut sunt Theologia, &amp; scientiae supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riores ut Astronomia &amp; Scientiae Prophetiae, &amp; Fidei; &amp; accident eis aegritudines, &amp; hominibus, dolores capitis, mors in animalibus cum mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tu ventorum calidorum venenosorum in quarta estivali; &amp; modico flatu in quarta au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>umnali; &amp; multiplicabuntur plavie in quarta hye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mali, &amp; significat multa tonitrua &amp; ventos horribiles destruentes reddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum &amp; praecipue in partibus meridionalibus multiplicabuntur messes in plu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>imis clim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tibus, &amp; erunt aborsus Praegnantium &amp; mors in Pueris, &amp; significat multitudinem fructuum hordei et dattilorum, cum salute Arborum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There will appeare in these Regions and Cities, where the People are subject to the Sign <hi>Gemini,</hi> too much consideration and conceit of their own Wisdomes, or too great an esteeme of their own judgements; yea, even of and in such things as seem to be above nature,<note place="margin">These must be expected the next Summer.</note> as in <hi>Theologie</hi> and in <hi>superiour Sciences, viz.</hi> kow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>Astronomie, Prophecy,</hi> Faith, men shall be troubled with infirmiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s in the head; death of Cattle shall succeed, many high Winds, sultry infections, or poysonous in the Summer quarter; little Winde in the Autumnall quarter; much Raine in the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter season; much Thunder; horrible Winds, destroying Mens yeerly Revenues, especially in the Southerne parts; store of Corn in many Climates; Women subject to many abortions; the death of Infants or yong Men; store of Dates or Barley, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son as to the Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and famine th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ned.</note>From hence we may conceive a doubtfull season as to the Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and not many over-plentifull crops of Corne (the whole scope of this Conjunction threatning a Dearth and Famine) I mean generally. I might be more copious, but the principall thing intended from this <hi>Conjunction,</hi> is, mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h affliction to those Families that had beginning in 1603. and since; it shewes not his Majesties restitution by words, tumultuous Petitions, or the Sword of the <hi>Scot;</hi> it doth not designe the failing, falling or dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution of this Parliament, or of his Excellencies Army, by or from the many clandestine Plots either of the City, <hi>Scot, English</hi> or <hi>Irish,</hi> or some, or any of their own Members.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Losse to the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens.</note>It intimates great losses and detriment unto the City of <hi>London,</hi> impoverishment of many of her Children, little Trade or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, want of provision, of Victuals, by reason of its excesse
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:116730:31"/> deernesse. I pray God it prove not a Plague, as well as a Famine.<note place="margin">The whole Kingdom invited to joyn with the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament and Army.</note> It is the resolution of my heart to serve God; and its my earnest desire, that as many of the Kingdom as either know me, or have any esteeme of my person or works, that they leave molesting the Parliament with unnecessary Petitions, that they stand firme, and as one man joyne with the Parliament and Army against all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posers; whereby they shall preserve the Liberty of this Kingdom, their own Priviledges; and, I hope, re-estate either his Majesty, if God have so decreed it, or some of his Posterity; how ever, I stand resolved with my whole heart to pray fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his Majesties re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storing to former Dignities, if God see it good; to serve the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and this Army now under the Command of his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> with all my strength and might, as the onely meanes upon earth to secure us and all our Fortunes: nor will I ever cease to wish all prosperity to the City and Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of <hi>London;</hi> unto whom, and unto the whole Kingdome, God for his mercies sake grant <hi>Peace,</hi> Prosperity, thankfull and obedient hearts:</p>
               <closer>
                  <hi>Being the strong wishes of</hi>
                  <signed>W. L.</signed>
                  <dateline>Finitur <date>
                        <hi>July</hi> 27. 1648.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="weather_forecast">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:116730:32"/>
               <head>A PROSPECT of the <hi>Weather</hi> for the Moneth of <hi>July</hi> 1648. next succeding this present <hi>Conjunction,</hi> as it was exactly observed.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>JUly</hi> the first, <hi>1648.</hi> A very lowring, thick, overcast Skie, and much Rain, the Winde Southwest.</p>
               <p>The second, great store of Rain the later part of the foregoing night, and this morning till six or seven a clock, the Winde very high and cold, and Northerly all day; the afternoon some comfortable Sun-shine, with some fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing clouds.</p>
               <p>The third, a very dark and gloomy drisling morning and forenoon, the Winde till that time Northerly and very cold; after one a clock in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, glorious and warm Weather, in respect of what it hath been a long time, the Winde Westerly; towards seven of the clock at night, the Ayre again overcast and dark, but very calm, and no probability of ill Weather.</p>
               <p>The fourth, the morning and forenoon dark, druggy Weather, and so un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till about six in the evening, when it began somewhat to cleer up, the Winde Northerly all day, and very cool.</p>
               <p>The fifth, the morning and forenoon much like the last day, about two in the afternoon it cleered up, and proved brave Weather, the Winde Northerly all day.</p>
               <p>The sixth, fine Weather in the morning, and till about ten of the clock, the rest of the day overcast, dark Weather, and much drisling and Rain, the Winde Westerly.</p>
               <p>The seventh, divers Showrs, and sometimes Sun-shine, but for the most part a clouded threatning Skie, the Winde Northwest.</p>
               <p>The eighth day the forenoon somewhat cloudy and lowring, but no Rain; after two of the clock brave cleer Weather, the Winde Northwest.</p>
               <p>The ninth, cloudy gloomy Weather all day, and good store of Rain in the afternoon, the Winde Southwest, and toward night removed somewhat Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly.</p>
               <p>The tenth, sometimes much overcast, sometimes very cleer and warm, dry all day; the winde Northwest.</p>
               <p>The eleventh, dry (warm) weather, though many times very threatning Clouds, the winde westerly.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:116730:32"/>
               <p>The twelfth, fine seasonable weather, very warm and dry, the winde westerly.</p>
               <p>The thirteenth; fair and very warm weather, the winde westerly.</p>
               <p>The fourteenth, the morning somewhat close, till about ten of the clock, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward very brave Hay-weather; the winde easterly, a fine fresh gale.</p>
               <p>The fifteenth, close, dark weather, threatning Rain, yet it held pretty dry; the winde Southeast, &amp;c. some smurring towards night.</p>
               <p>The sixteenth, an obscure close Ayre, some Rain, but not in abundance, gentle, still gales of winde, and it South.</p>
               <p>The seventeenth, a louring, dark morning, the windes high and boysterous, after noon some drops of Rain, the winde South.</p>
               <p>The eighteenth a fair, cleer Ayre, but little Sun-shine, the winde whistling very high westerly.</p>
               <p>The nineteenth, a gloomy day, thick clouds, no Sun-shine, pretty cool, and the winde high, west.</p>
               <p>The twentieth, the weather wholly corresponding with the former day, sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving now and then the Sun broke forth; the winde west.</p>
               <p>The <hi>21.</hi> day, a cleer Sun shine day, very calm and temperate, no excesse either in Winde or Sun-shine; the winde west.</p>
               <p>The <hi>22.</hi> a drowsie, drisling morning, cool Ayre, threatning moysture, the winde very high, and west, or a little Northwest.</p>
               <p>The <hi>23.</hi> a very cool morning, the Ayre windy, and flying clouds dispersing to severall quarters, after noon some drops of Rain, now and then the Sun shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning waterishly; the winde West.</p>
               <p>The <hi>24.</hi> a sharp, cool Ayre, yet much Sun-shine, the winde tumbling and high, and it west and by north.</p>
               <p>The <hi>25.</hi> a temperate dry Ayre, the Sun-shining very cleer; the winde west, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>26.</hi> a very warm sun-shine day, no winde appearing, all things calm and serene, the winde standing southwest.</p>
               <p>The <hi>27.</hi> a windy whirling season, yet the Ayre temperate, and a fair sun-shine; the winde west.</p>
               <p>The <hi>28.</hi> a very cleer day much sun-shine, the winde west.</p>
               <p>The <hi>29.</hi> Very little sun-shine, a gloomy cold morning, and so the cold con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing all day; the winde east.</p>
               <p>The <hi>30.</hi> a few drops in the afternoon, else a temperate windy day, and southeast.</p>
               <p>The <hi>31.</hi> A little windy, and very cool Ayre untill noon, then Rain, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the windes rose high, continuing southwest.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:116730:33"/>
               <head>The NATIVITY of <hi>Duke</hi> HAMILTON.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>astrological chart</figDesc>
                  <head>Duke-Hamilton: Borne: ♂ Iune 17<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. 21: 33 P. M 1606 <hi>Latt:</hi> 56</head>
               </figure>
               <p>HIS Majesty, were he any way inclinable to <hi>Astrologie,</hi> and should see this mans <hi>Nativity,</hi> might well say unto him, And thou also <hi>James Hamilton,</hi> hast aspiring thoughts, and one day intendest to be a greater man, then bare <hi>James</hi> Duke <hi>Hamilton.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It's not possible his Majesty should be angry with me, or any of his Royall <hi>Race,</hi> that I intermedled with the fate of this man, for he hath been the most unthankfull and unfortunate man that lives, unto his Majesty and his Designs; and as to the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> how maliciously ingratefull he now appears, let the whole Kingdom, and all <hi>Europe</hi> judge at present, and Posterity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it in everlasting memory hereafter.</p>
               <p>He appeared so unthankfull, and did his Majesty so many dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>services, that in <hi>Oxford</hi> he stood committed by a generall consent
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:116730:33"/> of the King's Counsell;<note place="margin">His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties grace to <hi>Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi>
                  </note> and when his life might well and justly have been taken from him, his Majesty out of his gracious clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy did not permit it, but spared him, contrary to all mens advice, and onely sent him prisoner to <hi>Pendennis</hi> in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> where he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in durance, untill in 1646. our Parliaments forces released him; he came to <hi>London,</hi> and had other civilities from them; yet now in 1648. in requitall of their favours, he onely, yea,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hamilton</hi> unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the King and Kingdom.</note> he and his envious faction, have provoked the <hi>Scottish</hi> Nation to wave the Covenant, (no cause being given by us) to become perfideous, and to raise an offensive War, and to invade our Kingdom with a considerable Army; nay, to enter our Country with that Army, as in <hi>July</hi> last he did, to permit plundering, robbing, stealing, and all manner of insolencies against the <hi>English;</hi> himself being the Ringleader of this Army, or (if you will have it so) their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Generall: To the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> it self, he is most mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous, who having had the greatest part of his education here amongst us, and augmented his fortune exceedingly, by the boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his Prince, and some Monopolies and Revenues of his Place; yea married a princely woman of our Nation, had children by her: now I say, after this to invade us, and to make the quarrell betwixt us and the <hi>Scots</hi> irreconcilable, when as we were before well united. For these considerations I fear his sin is unpardonable as unto us <hi>English,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Verily his <hi>Nativity</hi> is not inconsiderable,<note place="margin">Judgment on his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity:</note> but a very promising one; doubtlesse his Stars incline him to atchieve very great Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, to soar high, and to adventure dangerously to obtain it: for having the <hi>Luminary</hi> of the time, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Sun,</hi> angular, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited in the tenth, the <hi>Moon</hi> in a sinister <hi>Sextile</hi> to <hi>Mercury</hi> Lord of his ascendant, and he placed very auspitiously in the mid-heaven, very neer unto many eminent (though turbulent) fixed Stars, of great magnitude; the Planet himself stationary unto Direction, reception also happening betwixt the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon,</hi> the <hi>Dragon's head</hi> in the ascendant, <hi>Venus, Jupiter, Mars</hi> and <hi>Saturn</hi> all in their own houses; these configurations well thought on, his own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction being also noble, and his Sovereign not living in <hi>Scotland,</hi> the people themselves a stubborn, stiffe necked people, apt to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions, deadly feudes, and to be rebellious againg their Prince: all these things rightly considered, might move a moderate <hi>Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loger</hi> (for such a one, I have heard by his own familiars, he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self is) to promise a smattering of Regality unto this <hi>Duke;</hi> I assure
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:116730:34"/> you, the Stars declare a fit capacity for such a thing, a minde suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently inclinable thereunto, a pretty ambition, or the like, unto that we call <hi>Soveraignty,</hi> or unto most high Designs: for we will expresse things in modest terms.</p>
               <p>It shall be now ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> part to discover whether he shall attain the thing desired,<note place="margin">Whether Duke <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milton</hi> shal obtain a Kingdom.</note> yea or no? <hi>viz.</hi> a Kingdom, which some of his own Nation have not failed publickly to write, he earnestly desires.</p>
               <p>In regard the three superiour Planets are all under the earth, and all retrograde, and that <hi>Saturn</hi> is in opposition to the <hi>Sun,</hi> both the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon</hi> peregrine, the <hi>Moon</hi> falling into the eighth house, <hi>ergo,</hi> the <hi>Luminaries</hi> shall not design, or do in present or in future any royall Dignity unto this <hi>Duke,</hi> or in plain terms, the Crown of <hi>Scotland;</hi> it's <hi>Mercury</hi> alone of all the Planets, because pofited in the tenth house, with that assistance he receives from the <hi>Moon,</hi> as also <hi>Oculus Tauri,</hi> neer the cusp of the tenth house, that hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hath advanced him to the severall Charges and Preferments he hath had in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland:</hi> So then we must in an <hi>Astrologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> judicature account the Planet <hi>Mercury</hi> his principall <hi>Sngnifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> of honour; you shall have our judgement therein, in pag. 623. of the <hi>Introduction</hi> what that may signifie.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">What <hi>Mercury</hi> signifies when he designs honour.</note>When <hi>Mercury</hi> hath signification of Honour, and aspects the <hi>Lumina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ies,</hi> Honours encrease speedily in the beginning, and do also continue for a while; but in the end, he shall partake of great difficulty in preserving them; for <hi>Mercury</hi> is an unstable Planet, &amp;c. Again, when <hi>Mercury</hi> is moderately fortified, he threatens ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine; yet the <hi>Native</hi> shall not fall totally, for his <hi>Ʋnderstanding</hi> shall preserve him. [This hath been in some measure exactly verified severall times in the passages of his life; for whenas the <hi>Duke</hi> hath formerly been suspected of treachery or disservice to his <hi>Majesty,</hi> and he questioned,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hamilton</hi> not born to be suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesfull in War.</note> he ever got off again by one trick of Wit or another, or by his Policy, and so evaded.] His Stars are totally unfortunae in poynt of Warfare; he neither can or shall ever per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form any action of Honour by Commands, as a Generall over <hi>Armies:</hi> let him be accounted (as he is) one who hath the greatest reach of humane Policy, for advance of his own proper Designs, of any man alive; yet therein will he never be succesfull, or so much happy, as that any honour, or good in the end shall accrew unto him thereby. I say no more, but that this very <hi>Duke</hi> is his <hi>Majesties</hi> worst enemy, both in Action and Councell, retards his <hi>Majesties</hi> Designs, and destroyes them, is not ordained ever to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:116730:34"/> his <hi>Majesty:</hi> Let the <hi>Prince</hi> beware of <hi>Hamilton's</hi> Councels;<note place="margin">He once hanged an <hi>English</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in <hi>Germany,</hi> one Mr. <hi>Geo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ge Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> as I am infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</note> unto <hi>Scotland</hi> he is a firebrand, to <hi>England</hi> a malicious enemy, to mankinde it self no friend. For a farewell I say unto him, The eight and fortieth yeer of his age will fatally afflict him, if the fury of the people spare him so long, or the rage of an incensed <hi>Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> slaughter him not sooner: he is very neer danger at present. In his eight and fortieth yeer, <hi>Luna</hi> is directed <hi>ad oppositum Martis,</hi> &amp;c. let himself see what it signifies.</p>
               <p>Since this was finished, God's Name be praised for it, his <hi>Duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship</hi> is wholly routed by the valiant and fortunate <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and he fled to the Mountains of <hi>Wales:</hi> Let him ever be so valiant and so fortunate, as to be well beaten, and to run away from the pursuit of our <hi>English</hi> Armies.</p>
               <p>His rout was the seventeenth, eighteenth and nineteenth of <hi>August</hi> 1648. to the glory of God be it wrote, and honour of <hi>Cromwell:</hi> Our Army under the Lieutenant-general being not nine thousand; <hi>Hamilton's</hi> one and twenty thousand. Thus God blesses Covenant breakers and perfideous men with shame and dishonor, and so he will ever I hope. If the <hi>Scots</hi> have any more stomack to fight, let them be sure their Duke <hi>Hamilton</hi> will make such a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall as we desire.</p>
               <p>I had some <hi>Astrologicall</hi> reasons to have inserted unto this present <hi>Discourse,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A <hi>Solar</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clips in 0. 3. of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer. June</hi> 10. 1648. designed their ruine</note> whereby I probably conjectured the downfal of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Army of the <hi>Scots:</hi> but because God hath already confounded them, I forbear to publish that piece of <hi>Astrologie:</hi> yet I give the <hi>Scottish</hi> Nation, so many of them as have not sold themselves to wickednesse, this Admonition.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="admonition">
                           <p>
                              <hi>SCOTLAND,</hi> thy good Angel hath now forsaken thee,<note place="margin">The fate of <hi>Scotlād</hi> if againe invade.</note> I well know all January and February last were spent in clande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine, nocturnall Consultations to destroy us; the Design then was brought to some maturity, but thy poverty could not perfect it without friends; thy Emissaries then and since laboured hard, both in London and Westminster, to comply with thee; God hath already in part, and will more hereafter scourge thy private English friends, even almost to poverty and destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; nor shalt thou ever en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>oy a soot of ground in <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> or come neer the City of York, in an hostile manner, for Yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>k
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:116730:35"/> shall be a very royal City.<note place="margin">A childe is now born, shall live and see <hi>York</hi> a most flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing City.</note> Invade us again, for so thou intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est, but then expect not so fair an enemy as <hi>CROMWEL,</hi> nor such fair quarter as now is given thee: Jockey, Jemmy, and Moggy thy she-souldier, must then all to the sword; and fire, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and destruction follows, even to the wals, and into the heart of <hi>EDENBURGH</hi> it self.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <hi>Sic dixit</hi>
                              <signed>Merlinus Anglicus.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the whole KINGDOM.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Countrey-men of England:</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>A Scandalous and lying sheet of Paper this Moneth of <hi>August</hi> 1648. issued forth from some impure Pen, greatly to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shonour of many worthy Members of the House of Commons, who therein are unjustly charged with severall sums of Money pretended to be given unto them by the Parliament. Although I am not ignorant how freely this Libell or Budget of Lyes is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted for truth, both in the City and Countrey, and how hard a matter it will be to divert the streame of mens fancies, already poysoned with pre-occupation; yet I am confident that what I shall informe unto our own Kingdome, being grounded upon sufficient arguments and undeniable truths, will abundantly sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie many mens judgements, and inforce a Recantation in all noble spirits of their former sinister misapprehensions against all these Members of Parliament whom I shall nominate (all Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the House, I neither can or dare, or will excuse.) In the name of God let the guilty suffer according to Merit, and those who justly deserve it; let the justice of the House of Commons cleer their Wals of all such impure Birds as have any way defiled the honour and esteem of a Parliament. In the behalfe of all these whom I mention, I professe sincerity, I flatter none, but write impartiall truths, nor am I obliged to any one man of these I name, even for civill curtesies, except unto <hi>Bolstrod Whitlocke,</hi> Esq; one of the honorable Commissioners for the great Seal, and <hi>Robert Reynolds</hi> Esq; formerly one of the Parliaments Commissioners in <hi>Ireland;</hi> besides these whom I vindicate, there are, I am assured,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:116730:35"/> many more who are innocent even of the least corruption; but having no direction from them, let some other Pen <hi>proceed to their defence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is one clause in the Libellers sheet, which is a generall Charge against all the Members of the House, I have thought good to check this notorious untruth in the first place; he saith thus:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Every Member of the House of Commons,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Charge.</note>
                  <hi>being in all</hi> 516. <hi>are by their own Order allowed four pounds</hi> per <hi>week a Man, which amounts to one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ten thousand pounds a yeer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tis true, that in <hi>June</hi> 1645.<note place="margin">Vindicat.</note> the House taking into considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the necessities of divers Members, many of them having their whole Estates lying in the Western parts, and for full three yeers together they had received no benefit out of them, the same being all that time under the power of the Enemy and actually seque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred, did Order upon the desires of many of them (who never askt as long as they could take up monies at interest upon their own credits) that they should have four pounds a week for the maintenance of them and their Families,<note place="margin">No Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament man had allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of 4 l. a week a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove one yeer.</note> out of the King and Queens revenues, who did then and all the time before, take and receive the profit of the Estates of the said Members, the which was granted to, and received by seventy three of them and no more, for one yeer onely, they refusing to receive it longer, their Estates being reduced unto them, the which allowance was never desired, given to, or received, either by the said <hi>Denzell Holles, Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund Prydeanx, Roger Hill, Francis Rowse, Nicholas Love, Dennis Bond, John Bond, Luke Hodges, John Stephens, John Ashe, Thomas Ceely, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Blake,</hi> or <hi>John Venn,</hi> whose whole estates then lay in the We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stern Counties, and were no wayes profitable to them during the whole time of the late troubles. This is the very truth imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally related; all the whole sum which these seventy three Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers had in one whole yeer not amounting unto fifteen thousand pounds, to maintain seventy three Families; many of these Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen being of that quality as formerly they expended yeerly out of their own Revenues some one thousand, some two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand pounds <hi>per annum.</hi> I appeal unto the whole Kingdome whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther these Members, who faithfully did their duties even in those ill times, and whom no worldly calamity or threats could inforce to desert the Publique <hi>Cause</hi> of the Common-wealth, have not well merited these petty sums the House conferd on them; not out of the Publique Stock (as the impudent lyer affirmes) but out
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:116730:36"/> of the Kings and Queens Revenues, who having these Mens E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states sequestred in their hands, were gainers annually of at least forty thousand pounds a yeer. You now see this mountain of Lyes, this one hundred and ten thousand pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> proves a little Mouse; a thing of fifteen thousand, and that but for one yeer, and not out of the Publique Treasury; and this Money con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred on such brave Spirits, whose Names deserve to be eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly recorded in the Monument of Fame, for being so faithfull and so constant to the Common-wealth, notwithstanding their world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pressures.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Charge.</note>
                  <hi>Bulstrode Whitlock, Commissioner of the great Seal, worth</hi> 1500. li. per an. <hi>and had</hi> 2009. li. <hi>given him out of Master</hi> George Minn's <hi>esttae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Vindicat.</note>Master <hi>Whitlock,</hi> (a Gentleman of much honour and gallantry) after his faithfull service performed in Parliament, and their ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, from the very beginning, and oftentimes adventuring his life for them, after his laying out of his own purse great sums of money upon severall occasions, in their service, and in four jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys upon Treaties for Peace, in some whereof the Parliament gave no allowance, and in the rest far short of the expence: in sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of those his great disbursments, and of his being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly plundered, his chief Mansion-house demolished, his Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue taken away for many yeers, his Estate disposed of by the Kings Party, and his losses amounting to the value of above ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand pounds, the Parliament were pleased to alow him two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand pounds out of Moneys seized upon by them:<note place="margin">He is a Counsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor at Law very lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and in great pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice.</note> They did like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise make him one of the Commissioners for the great Seal with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his knowledge, which is not of the value mentioned in the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and thereby took him from his employment in his profession, which was of more benefit to him, and from his future expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on therein.</p>
               <p>How willingly this <hi>Libeller</hi> would asperse any man of honour, it's evident, by his malicious urging such triviall matter unto this my noble Patron, as a blemish. This is that Master <hi>Whitlock,</hi> who in all Occasions, Consultations and Debates, so judiciously and modestly hath demeaned himself, and in his now place of <hi>Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> so equally distributes justice, that I challenge all the whole p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ck of malignant Scriblers, to mention, if they can, one syllable of his injustice: But upon so pure a soul, no dirt will fasten.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Charge.</note>Roger Hill, <hi>a Barrester of the Temple, in no practice, nor of a considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Estate, till this Parliament; hath now from the House, the Bishop of</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:116730:36"/> Winchester's <hi>Mannour of</hi> Taunton-Dean, <hi>being the best of</hi> England, <hi>and worth</hi> 12000. li. per an. <hi>when the Estates for lives determine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How injuriously this shuffling fellow deals with Master <hi>Roger Hill,</hi> I shall make it presently appear:<note place="margin">Vindicat.</note> This Master <hi>Hill</hi> had before this Parliament as good practic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as any of his standing, and was one of a considerable fortune in money; and it's well known that in 1640. he contracted with Sir <hi>Aribur Ingram,</hi> for a Mannour in <hi>Dorsetshire,</hi> and was to pay for it more money then half the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase of <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unton-Dean:</hi> but that bargain not going forward, he now hath purchased at most dear rates <hi>Taunton-Dean;</hi> yet not all the Mannour, but part of the bare Rents and Casualties never to be improved: The income of all the whole Rents, as it's returned from the Records themselves, are under 900. li. <hi>per an.</hi> It's also well known, that Master <hi>Hill</hi> hath the Park (anciently belonging to the said Mannour) by descent from his Father, whose Ancestors almost two hundred yeers have injoyed the same, being purchased by them from the Bishop that then was, and severed from the Mannour; so that above twelve parts of thirteen of this <hi>Libeller's</hi> yeerly value is taken off, and he stands recorded for a grosse Lyar and Incendiary, whose sole ayme is to dishonour those Members who have most cordially stood firm unto this Parliament, as this Master <hi>Hill</hi> hath done, to his very great honour, and everlasting renown. By what I have wrote, you finde Master <hi>Hill</hi> abused, and the Parliament charged with manifest untruth; for a <hi>Turk</hi> or a <hi>Scot</hi> might have had the purchase of <hi>Taunton-Dean</hi> at as easie rates as Master <hi>Hill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oliver St. John, <hi>by Ordinance both Attorney, and Solicitor to the King,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Charge.</note>
                  <hi>worth what he please to make it; and hath rhe passing of all Pardons upon Compositions; worth</hi> 40000. li.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oliver St. John,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vindicat.</note> neither Attorny nor Solicitor by Ordinance of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; and if the Pardons had come to 40000. l. he could have had it by vertue of his Place, though no Member of Parliament; &amp; he would be beholding to the forger of the List, if he could make it appear, that much more then a fortieth part of 40000. li. hath been received, or is due for such Pardons; and the slanderer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self knows, that by reason of his attendance on the Parliament, and the distractions of the time, his Place is not at all conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, to what it would have been without a Parliament, or hath been to his Predecessors, who have made more of it in one yeer, then he hath done in seven. But the Common-wealth
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:116730:37"/> might have been beholding to this great pretender of their good, if he had acquainted them with any illegall or unjust vexations of the Subject by him done, by colour of his Place; which perhaps some of his Predecessors have been guilty of.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Charge.</note>Francis Thorp, <hi>a receiver of publike moneys in</hi> Yorkshire, <hi>and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by some of his Countreymen for detaining</hi> 25000. li.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Vindicat.</note>
                  <hi>Francis Thorp</hi> was never receiver of any publike moneys in <hi>York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire,</hi> nor in any other place; nor did he ever buy, purchase, or farm any thing of the State; nor hath he ever received 4. li. <hi>per</hi> week, or any other sum from the State: and therefore he is confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent none of his countreymen will charge him, and is very sure none can justly charge him with detaining either 25000. li. or any other sum to the value of a shilling.</p>
               <p>What a villanous Incendiary is this <hi>Libeller,</hi> thus to traduce this worthy man with so hainous and so false untruths; but it's scandall enough against any man, that he stand firm to his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Charge.</note>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Thomas Widrington, <hi>a Commissioner of the great Seal; worth</hi> 1500 l. <hi>per an.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Vindicat.</note>All the North of <hi>England</hi> know the integrity and justnesse of this Knight, and we in the South doe well know the benefit of his practice, before the Houses made him a Commissioner of the great Seal, did far surmount the Annuall sum this Lyer menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as conferd on him by the Houses.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Charge.</note>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Gilbert Gerrard, <hi>much in debt before the Parliament; pay-master to the Army, and had</hi> 3<seg rend="sup">d</seg>. per <hi>pound allowed, besides Gratuities; worth</hi> 60000<seg rend="sup">l</seg>. <hi>and now Chancellor of the Dutchey; worth</hi> 1200<seg rend="sup">l</seg>. per an.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Vindicat.</note>The whole County of <hi>Middlesex</hi> can informe this absurd Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that Sir <hi>Gilbert Gerrard</hi> was neither indebted or necessitated for moneys before the Parliament; and how little benefit he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by his being Treasurer; or his allowance of 3.d. <hi>per</hi> pound, it is publikely known, more then 1000. li. for all his 3. d. <hi>per</hi> pound, I could never learn he received: He is too noble, and too much a Gentleman to receive gratuities; but in doing curtesies to his friends, and in affection to the common good, he is inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or to none: Being charged with threescore thousand pounds; loe, but one appeares: he is now its true Chancellour of the Dutchie, <hi>Nomen sine re;</hi> I am confident, it hath not hitherto bin worth to him so much money as would buy halters to hang up a dozen of such scandalous Lyers.</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:116730:37"/>
               <p>John Bond (<hi>son to</hi> Dennis Bond,<note place="margin">Charge.</note>
                  <hi>a Parliament man) made Master of Trinity hall in</hi> Cambridge, <hi>which Master</hi> Selden <hi>refused to accept of.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Master <hi>John Bond</hi> hath the repute of a learned man,<note place="margin">Vindicat.</note> and is made Master of <hi>Trinity hall,</hi> which Master <hi>Selden</hi> refused to accept of: this is a grand offence for one Scholler to be preferred in the room of another; <hi>Don Quixote</hi> doubtlesse was of councell in framing this information.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Thomas Walsingham, <hi>the honour of</hi> Eltham,<note place="margin">Charge.</note>
                  <hi>that was the Earl of</hi> Dorsets, <hi>the middle Park and house, which was Master</hi> Whites, <hi>and hath cut down</hi> 4000. <hi>timber trees.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Thomas Walsingham</hi> is most unjustly charged to have cut down 4000. timber trees out of his Majesties Woods: one <hi>Bently,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vindicat.</note> Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyor of his Majesties Lands, hath publickly affirmed in print that the totall of the Wood sales from Midsommer 1644. till Midsom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer 1648. amounts to 602. l. and so much he makes it appear he hath paid in to the Receivers: though <hi>Bently</hi> was formerly a Scrivener, yet sure he may now be beleeved. If 4000. timber trees had been cut down and sold, the price thereof would have amounted to more then three times the sum <hi>Bently</hi> mentions.</p>
               <p>Robert Reynolds <hi>had</hi> 2000. l. <hi>given him; besides</hi> Abingdon hall,<note place="margin">Charge.</note>
                  <hi>and the Lands, worth</hi> 400. l. per an. <hi>Hath bought a good peniworth of Bishops Lands; hath</hi> 20000. l. <hi>beyond Sea, as he made appear upon his marriage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Master <hi>Reynolds</hi> hath served from the first beginning of this Parliament, was sent one of the Committee into <hi>Ireland,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vindicat.</note> in <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> 1642. where he conflicted with indefatigable pains, in promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the War against the Rebels for five moneths, to the exream h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zard of his life, both by Sea and Land, hath been out of purse above 1800. l. in ready money, these six yeers, for the service of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> and by taking away the <hi>Court of Wards,</hi> hath lost 800. l. <hi>per an.</hi> at the least; in his practice. For all which ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and sufferings, he is rewarded with this groundlesse malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous falshood: namely, <hi>That the Parliament hath given him</hi> 2000. l. <hi>in money, and</hi> Abingdon Hall, <hi>worth</hi> 400. l. per an. Meer lyes and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geries; <hi>And that he hath</hi> 20000. l. <hi>in money beyond the Seas:</hi> of all which there is not one word true, or that hath any colour of truth. And for his good peniworth of Bishops Lands, which he is there said to have over and above; it was so good in his esteem, that when he had contracted for it, he would not have gone on with his bargain, had he not been compelled thereto by an Ordinance of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:116730:38"/> Parliament, and offered both before the Contractors and Trustees for Bishops Lands, to give 500. l. to any one that would take his purchase from off his hands; neither ever had he any Office or employment of advantage by the Parliament. The truth of all which I do undertake to make good to a title: And by the scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall cast upon this Gentleman, who hath thus faithfully served the Parliament, the world may judge what credit is to be given to that malicious Libeller, in those things he hath belched out against many worthy Members, on purpose to wound the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whose honour ought to be precious amongst all true <hi>English</hi> men.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Charge.</note>John Ash, <hi>given him out of Master</hi> John Coventrey's <hi>Composition,</hi> 4000. l. <hi>out of Sir</hi> Edward Moseley's, 1000. l. <hi>out of Master</hi> Edward Phillip's 1200. l. <hi>out of Sir</hi> John Stowel's <hi>estate</hi> 8000. l. <hi>And (which is worth all this) is the great Chair-man at Goldsmiths Hall.</hi> Is not this better then clothing?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Vindicat.</note>About three yeers since, there was presented to the house of Commons an account of 10900 l. which Master <hi>Denzill Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> Master <hi>Nathaniel Fiennes,</hi> Colonel <hi>Popham,</hi> Colonel <hi>Strode,</hi> and Master <hi>John Ash,</hi> had disbursed for the service of the Parliament at <hi>Sherburn, Bristoll,</hi> and in the County of <hi>Somerset,</hi> when the Earl of <hi>Bedford</hi> came with an Army into those parts: most of which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney was borrowed upon Bond of some Citizens of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> and Gentlemen of that Countrey, by the Gentlemen above named, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with other Gentlemen of the County of <hi>Somerset;</hi> the house of Commons did order, that out of the fines and compositions of Sir <hi>John Stowell,</hi> Sir <hi>Edward Moseley,</hi> and Master <hi>John Coventrey,</hi> the said disbursments and engagements should be discharged, and Master <hi>John Ash</hi> was ordered to receive the money, and to discharge the disbursments and take up the Bonds: and of this 10900. l. there hath been paid onely 7400. l. by Sir <hi>Edward Mosely,</hi> and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster <hi>Coventry;</hi> which money hath been employed according to the foresaid order; Sir <hi>John Stowell</hi> refusing to compound, there hath not been one penny received out of his Estate by Master <hi>John Ash;</hi> and by reason thereof, there is unpaid 3500. l. of the said engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: The Creditors to whom the same is due, call upon Master <hi>Ash</hi> for their money, and he is daily solicited and clamoured up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the same: and this is all the benefit that he hath gained by the said fines and great sums received; though that foul scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:116730:38"/> paper doth charge him with a great gift of 14000. l. which is notoriously false, the matter in truth being as abovesaid: Master <hi>Colborn</hi> a Scrivener in Budge-row, hath been employed by Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Mosely</hi> to provide some part of his fine, and he can inform to whom the same was assigned by Master <hi>Ash,</hi> for the discharge of the said Order of the house of Commons.</p>
               <p>And whereas he objects, his being Chair-man at Goldsmiths Hall, as a blemish; could but this sneaking Lyar have heard one syllable of sinister dealing in Master <hi>Ash,</hi> I am confident he would have preacht it abroad merily; but his fair deportment and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity is such in that place, as none complain: so that he may justly bid defiance to the Devil, and to such Hell-hounds as this Informer.</p>
               <p>Francis Pierpoint <hi>hath the Archbishop of Yorks Lands lying in Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinghamshire.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Charge.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Francis Pierpoint</hi> Esq; hath no Bishops Lands.<note place="margin">Vindicat.</note>
               </p>
               <p>William Pierpoint <hi>hath seven thousand pounds given him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Charge.</note>
                  <hi>and all the Earl of Kingstons personall Estate, worth</hi> 40000 <seg rend="sup">l</seg>.<note place="margin">Vindicat.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Pierpoint</hi> Esq; hath no Bishops Lands given to him, but he did for a valuable consideration in money by him paid, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase part of the Lands belonging to the late Archbishop of <hi>Yorke</hi> in Nottinghamshire.</p>
               <p>Both Houses of Parliament have given the Fine of <hi>Henry</hi> Earle of <hi>Kingston</hi> of neer seven thousand pounds set at <hi>Goldsmiths-Hall</hi> to his Brother <hi>William Pierpoint,</hi> in consideration of above twenty thousand pounds, by him lost for the service of the Parliament. And for that the said Earl his Brother had but an Estate for Life in his Lands, the next immediate remainder being in the said <hi>William Pierpoint.</hi> So as else in truth, the Fine, if paid, must have been paid by the Lands of the said <hi>William Pierpoint,</hi> the said <hi>Henry</hi> Earl of <hi>Kingston</hi> having no personall Estate, and his Debts deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in at <hi>Gol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>smith Hall</hi> to be above 19000 <seg rend="sup">l</seg>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Pierpoint</hi> had also given him by the Parliament a Coach and six Horses of his said Brothers the Earl of <hi>Kingston,</hi> which is all whatsoever that hath been given to him by the Parliament.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Pierpoint</hi> had no part of the personall Estate of <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Kingston</hi> his Father.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Francis Pierpoint</hi> was made Executor by the last will of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Kingston,</hi> and by order of Parliament was to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:116730:39"/> have the benefit of the Executorship, which by reason of these times hath been of little value to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Charge.</note>Oliver Cromwell, <hi>Lievtenant Generall, hath</hi> 2500 <seg rend="sup">l</seg>. per an. <hi>given him out of the Marquesse of</hi> Worcesters <hi>Estate, for which</hi> 4000 <seg rend="sup">l</seg>. per an. <hi>is set out at the rate of</hi> 2500 <seg rend="sup">l</seg>.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Vindicat.</note>Lievtenant Generall <hi>Cromwell</hi> hath 1500 <seg rend="sup">l</seg>. a yeer assigned him of the Earl of <hi>Worcesters</hi> Estate. He had spent a great part of his own Estate while he attended the Publique service in the Armies, &amp;c. It was the free gift of the House without his seeking. And when the House had passed it; he freely gave to the service of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> 1000 <seg rend="sup">l</seg>. <hi>per an.</hi> for five yeers to come, if he shall live so long, and the War of <hi>Ireland</hi> so long continue, to be paid half yeerly, and the first 500 <seg rend="sup">l</seg>. to be paid out of the <hi>Michaelmas</hi> rents now next coming; and of this all the Gentlemen of <hi>Ireland</hi> here in Town can be witnesse; who the next day after he had made this offer in the House, came to his Lodging to give him a solemn thanks for it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Charge.</note>John Birch, <hi>formerly a Carrier; now a Collonel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Vindicat.</note>The next mentioned in your List is Collonel <hi>John Birch,</hi> of whom you onely say he was sometimes a Carrier, but now a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell. A very short Charge, and to judicious men a great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, where your invenomed Pen can throw no great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation; but because you have so little knowledge of him, give me leave a word or two.</p>
               <p>This is that Collonel <hi>Birch,</hi> who for his manner of life, before this time of Warre, followed Merchandizing in the West of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> living in <hi>Bristoll;</hi> and had occasion to deal in Goods brought from most parts of this Kingdome; I suppose therefore you cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him a Carrier; yet this Carrier, if so you call him, when Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the Liberty of the Subject, and Priviledge of Parliament were in danger, at severall times supplied the Parliament or their Armies with two thousand pounds at a time at least; and of his own particular was out for them one and twenty hundred pounds before he ever drew sword in the quarrell; but when he saw that would not serve, he hazarded his person in all conditions, from a Captain to a Collonel, and Commander of a Brigade by which meanes he carried you out of divers good Towns. And Gratitude would have put you in minde, rather to have given him thanks
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:116730:39"/> for sparing so many of your lives, which were at his mercy.</p>
               <p>It seems you charge him with no Office, onely he is a Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel; you have reason to curse the day he had that Office; and though he have no more then the name of a Collonell at present, yet rather then the old cause shall want assistance, I have reason to be confident, you will have the second part to the same Tune.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> William Purefoy, <hi>Collonell, and Governour of</hi> Coventry,<note place="margin">Charge.</note>
                  <hi>fought resolutely against the crosse in the Market-place at</hi> Warwicke, <hi>and against the ancient Monuments in the Earls Chappell in St.</hi> Maries <hi>Church there; for which he had</hi> 1500 <seg rend="sup">l</seg>. <hi>given him; but when he should have fought with the Enemy, hid himselfe in a Barley-field; for which a Water-man at Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple-stairs, (that had bin his Souldier) refused to carry him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vindicat.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The late Earl of <hi>Essex</hi> in his Martch to relieve <hi>Glocester,</hi> sent his Orders to Collonell <hi>William Purefoy</hi> to meet him in the way with five hundred Horse, under his Command; the Collonell enters <hi>Cambden,</hi> intending there to quarter, but having five seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall advisoes by his Scouts and others, that the whole body of the Enemies Horse were quartered within four miles, and had know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his being in <hi>Cambden;</hi> a Counsell of War being called, it was agreed to remove into the Fields adjacent to the Town; and so they did, and there were Cocks of Barley there, wherewith the Horse were refreshed. The Enemy within two hours entred the Town with two thousand Horse, intending to have surprised them; but missing their Design presently retreated. This is all Corn-fields or Cocks of Barley the Collonell ever remembers; and herein he is much to be commended for his discretion. He was never Governour of <hi>Coventry:</hi> and for wronging of Tombs or Monuments of antiquity at <hi>Warwicke</hi> or elsewhere; its false and untrue; he hath too much extraction of noble blood in him, to doe the least wrong to their Memorials. For the one thousand five hundred pounds mentioned; its true, he had so much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, but it was according to the allowance other Commanders of his quality had; his just due came to two thousand five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds, but he willingly accepted of one thousand five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds, and quit the thousand pounds to the State. This is the very truth.</p>
               <p>Thomas Westrow, <hi>Captain under Sir</hi> Michael Livesey,<note place="margin">Charge.</note>
                  <hi>was nothing worth, untill a Captain and Parliament man; and now hath gotten the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:116730:40"/> of</hi> Worcester's <hi>Mannour of</hi> Hartlerow, <hi>which proves he hath two good and beneficiall Offices.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Vindicat.</note>Captain <hi>Westrow</hi> having a trained Troop in <hi>Kent,</hi> went out with Sir <hi>Michael Livesey,</hi> and some other Deputy-Lievtenants of that County, to help their neighbours of <hi>Surrey</hi> and <hi>Sussex</hi> upon a pinch; and having before given and lent above four hundred pounds to the Parliaments service, was willing to have the spend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of some money that way himself, and therefore for the more speedy compleating of his Troop, contributed many Horse and Arms, beside new coats to each of the Riders; and the Enemy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wholly broken at <hi>Aulton</hi> and <hi>Arundel,</hi> and those Countries quit, he return<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d home, when he had spent neer two hundred pounds more then his pay. He bought <hi>Hartlebury,</hi> belonging for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly to the Bishop of <hi>Worcester,</hi> about <hi>August</hi> last, for a valuable consideration, to countenance that businesse, when few else durst meddle with Bishops Lands.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Charge.</note>Nathaniel Fiennes, <hi>Colonel, once Governour of</hi> Bristol, <hi>Thereby hangs a tail.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Vindicat.</note>Master <hi>Nathaniel Fiennes,</hi> for his pains and services of all kindes, for these eight yeers, never received any thing by way of compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation, or of his Arrears, or of the weekly allowance given to others, though he was plundered, and his Estate lay a long time under the power of the enemy: and for his being once Colonel and Governour of <hi>Bristol,</hi> and the tail at the end thereof, there is none now but such as are wholly made up of envy and malice, who is not satisfied, that it is onely a tail of malicious lyes and slanders, wherein God himself, the righteous Judge hath vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him. But the malignant Author of that List, should have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought himself, that there is another tail at the end of that tail, which reacheth indeed their once great Generall Prince <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert,</hi> Plunder-master not of <hi>Kent</hi> or <hi>Surrey,</hi> but Plunder-master generall of all <hi>England,</hi> who hath got more by the sad calamities of this Kingdom, caused by him, and those of his Party, then all he Members of Parliament put together.</p>
               <p>Besides these untruths alleaged against the persons before named, he mentions many Offices to be conferred by the Parliament on
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:116730:40"/> their Members, which they enjoy by Patent under his Majesty, and not by any gift of the Parliament, were I not straightned in time I could vindicate most of the Members in this first <hi>Century;</hi> for where this Libeller stumbles upon one truth, he tels forty lyes for it; and where he mentions large sums conferred on some and not received; you must understand those Members smell on his owne Faction; for I know they have received part, &amp;c. All I ayme at, is to informe the Kingdome rightly, which in what I have now done shall be justified against all opposition. I wish there was no cause of complaints against some; but to condemn the upright and vertuous without hearing; or equally to accuse all, is certainly a peece of great injustice. The Members of the Houses now seeing themselves not spared, I hope will hereafter be sensible of the reproaches those few friends they have left are subject unto by abusive Pamphlets, and yet no order taken for suppression.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>